<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lathams new and second booke of falconrie concerning the training vp of all hawkes that were vnmentioned in his first booke of the haggart faulcon and gerfaulcon, formerly printed; teaching approued medicines for all their diseases. / By Symon Latham, Gent.</title>
            <title>Lathams falconry. Book 2</title>
            <author>Latham, Simon.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 229 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 87 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05138</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15268.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15268_PARTIAL_FORMER</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108357</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844016</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844016</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26902</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05138)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26902)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 804:1b, 1835:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Lathams new and second booke of falconrie concerning the training vp of all hawkes that were vnmentioned in his first booke of the haggart faulcon and gerfaulcon, formerly printed; teaching approued medicines for all their diseases. / By Symon Latham, Gent.</title>
                  <title>Lathams falconry. Book 2</title>
                  <author>Latham, Simon.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 148, [4] p. : ill. (woodcuts)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I.B. for Roger Iackson, and are to be sold at his shop neere Fleet-Conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printed by John Beale. Cf. STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for a fleuron; the last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>With a final epilogue leaf.</note>
                  <note>Usually found bound with the 1615 variant of the first book (STC 15267.3).</note>
                  <note>Formerly identified as part 2 of STC 15268.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 804 and at reel 1835 (same copy filmed twice).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Falconry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Birds --  Diseases --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26902:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>LATHAMS NEW AND SECOND Booke of FALCONRY; concerning the ordering and trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vp of all ſuch HAWKES as was omitted or left vnmentioned in his printed Booke of the HAGGARD FALCON and GERFALCON, namely, the <hi>Goſhawke</hi> and <hi>Taſſell,</hi> with the <hi>Sparhawke,</hi> the <hi>Lanner</hi> and <hi>Lanneret,</hi> as they are diuided in their generation: the <hi>Hobby</hi> and <hi>Marlyn</hi> in their kindes: Teaching approued Medicines for all ſuch infirmities and diſeaſes as are inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to them.</p>
            <p>¶ Publiſhed for the delight of Noble mindes, and inſtruction of yong <hi>Falconers</hi> in all things per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to this Art.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed by <hi>I. B.</hi> for <hi>Roger Iackſon,</hi> and are to bee ſold at his ſhop neere Fleet Conduit. 1618.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26902:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26902:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>FAVLCON</head>
                     <p>1. booke.</p>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>GOSHAWKE.</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>SPAROWHAWKE</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure/>
                  <figure/>
                  <figure>
                     <p>LATHAMS new and ſecond Booke of Falconrie, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the training vp of all HAWKES that were vnmentioned in his firſt Booke of the HAGGART FAVLCON and GER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FAVLCON, formerly printed; teaching appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Medicines for all their diſeaſes.</p>
                     <p>By <hi>SYMON LATHAM,</hi> Gent</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>AT LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>I. B.</hi> for <hi>Roger Iackson,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop neere Fleet-Conduit, 1618,</p>
                  </figure>
                  <figure/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>GERFAVLCO<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </head>
                     <p>1. booke.</p>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>LANNER.</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>HOBBY.</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>MERLIN.</head>
                  </figure>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:26902:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26902:3"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the right VVorſhipfull and Noble-minded Gentleman S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Patrick Hume</hi> Knight, <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Falconer to the Kings moſt excellent Maieſtie:</hi> S. L. wiſheth all increaſe of Honors in this life, and eternall happineſſe in the world to come.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>WORTHY SIR:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He wings of my vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing Muſe (impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued on with the good o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of her <hi>Patron</hi>) heretofore preſumed to ſo are Hawke-hie; yet as then I ſpake particular: but now (as well for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation of the noble ſport, as for the explanation of the effects of nature) J preſume to dedicate to your noble Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in that ſport, a generalitie of defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions in <hi>Hawks,</hi> both in Names &amp; Natures: the perfection of my paines (like a Diamond ſet in gold) reſts in
<pb facs="tcp:26902:4"/>
the truth of your opinion. And as in the naturall motion of the heauens, the greater circumference euer moues the leſſer; ſo (I make no queſtion) if your deſeruing iudgement giue me approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, all other cenſures will conſequently leuill with your Ayme: I ſo far tooke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance of preſumption to chuſe you for my Patron, being aſſured your Judgement will giue a more luſter to my labours. Vertue J doe make my Miſtris; and finding her keepe open houſe in your addicted inclination; I thought no toyle laborious to attain reſt in ſuch a harbor. Jf your charitie refuſe to patronize this poore expresſion of a well wiſher, J wiſh it had been ſtill borne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but my hope is, your noble Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture will both giue it life, and nouriſh it; for which I ſhall euer reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Not more deuoted then indebted to your vertue, S. L.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:26902:4"/>
            <head>To the Courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is now foure yeeres paſt (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) ſince importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by ſome of my ſpeciall friends, J tooke vpon me in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of their earneſt requeſt, to write my firſt Booke of the <hi>Haggart Falcon Gentle;</hi> for which they then ſhewed me many lykelyhoods and reaſons how much the ſame might profit; and how well of diuers ſorts of people, eſpecially of yong men and learners, the
<pb facs="tcp:26902:5"/>
labour might be accepted. Neuertheleſſe, by aduertiſement of the Printers, and alſo through the report of others, I haue vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the contrarie; and that being but as it were a booke in particular, treating of on <hi>Hawke,</hi> it was refuſed and ſlightly accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of by many; whoſe wils and affections were formerly fixed on other ſubiects. For which cauſe I haue here, although vnskillfully and vnwiſely, vndertaken a courſe quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to my owne diſpoſition, and altogether diſagreeing with my former will and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; as vnto things for the moſt part of little or no deſeruing, to preſcribe rules of Art, words of praiſe and commendation. Yet on the former conſiderations, as alſo at the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſute and reimportunitie of my friends, I doe intend to perſeuere in my purpoſe, and in a ſhort Treatiſe once againe to lay downe a <hi>Hawke,</hi> not as the onely ſubiect of my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Art, but a worke of my deuice. And the <hi>Goſhawke</hi> is ſhee, the which I am determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſpeake of, with ſhew and declaration of her properties and nature; and generally of all ſuch other <hi>Hawks</hi> as were omitted, and are
<pb facs="tcp:26902:5"/>
amongſt vs ordinary at this preſent day, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the <hi>Taſſell</hi> of the <hi>Goſhawke,</hi> the <hi>Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hawke,</hi> and her excellent properties; the <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> and <hi>Lanneret,</hi> as they are deuided in their kindes, the <hi>Hobby,</hi> and the <hi>marlin;</hi> the one belonging to the yong man; the other pertaining to the Ladie. But firſt, I purpoſe to begin with the <hi>Oſtringer</hi> him ſelfe, and with his <hi>Hawke</hi> as ſhee is wilde, compared with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fowles of the ayre; and of their naturall awe they haue of the man, and fearfulneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all other creatures. Secondly, of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyell,</hi> and the ſocietie there ought to bee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the man, the <hi>Hawke,</hi> and him ſelfe. Thirdly, with directions to the <hi>Oſtringer,</hi> and inſtructions to the nouice. Fourthly, of the difference in the manner of flying of the <hi>Goſhawke</hi> compared with the longwinged <hi>Hawke,</hi> which the <hi>Oſtringer</hi> ought to obſerue. Fiftly, of the <hi>Goſhawke,</hi> compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the <hi>Lanner,</hi> for her ſoundneſſe and long laſting; the which dependeth vpon the well or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering and gouerning of her keeper. And laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, how the beſt and ſkilfulleſt <hi>Oſtringer</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:26902:6"/>
ought to ioyne both care and continuall attendance with his beſt skill and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, to preſerue his <hi>Hawkes</hi> health and life withall.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <head>An acknowledgment of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors loue and thankefullneſſe to his firſt Maiſter and founder.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd furthermore, let mee condemne my ſelfe of former forgetfulneſſe, and not bee vnmindfull againe of the right worſhipfull maiſter <hi>Henrie Sadler</hi> of Euerly, who was my firſt and louing maiſter, and from whom I had my art and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding kindly ſhewed mee, obſcuring no rules or skill from mee, wherein hee was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing inferior then to any gentleman what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer of his reputation or reckoning. Hee, I confeſſe, it was that taught mee the way to liue, although I had had no other meanes:
<pb facs="tcp:26902:6"/>
For which, in all loue and thankefullneſſe, I ſubmit my ſelfe vnto him, and (if he be yet liuing) ought alſo dayly to pray for him, ſo long as it ſhall pleaſe God to alot him time in this world.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:26902:7"/>
            <head>Jn commendation of the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor and his Booke.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>NAture a Table of delightfull cates,</l>
            <l>Hath richly furniſh'd out for all eſtates.</l>
            <l>He is a ſullen gueſt, that when he may</l>
            <l>Feed at his choyce, hungrie departs away.</l>
            <l>Hawking is one faire Diſh, if rich men would</l>
            <l>Vſe it, not as they doe, but as they ſhould.</l>
            <l>But becauſe circumſtances make or marre</l>
            <l>Pleaſure, that in themſelues indifferent are:</l>
            <l>Wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g not your ſelues in that which you allow;</l>
            <l>Which to obſerue you may heere ſtudie how.</l>
            <l>Conſult it, practiſe it: and ſo you ſhall</l>
            <l>Well man your <hi>Hawkes,</hi> manage your ſelues withal.</l>
            <l>Neuer hath Engliſh man in publike ſort</l>
            <l>Giuen fairer orders for ſo noble ſport.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. A.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:26902:7"/>
            <head>A TABLE OF the Chapters and PRINCIPALL MAT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TERS CONTAINED in this Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F the <hi>Oſtringer,</hi> and first of the <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hawke</hi> compared with other Fowles of the ayre, as they are vnreclaimed and wilde, and of the awe and feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe they haue of the man aboue all other creatures. page <hi>1</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <item>Of the <hi>Spaniell,</hi> and the ſocietie there ought to bee betweene the man, the <hi>Hawke</hi> and himſelfe. p. <hi>3.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:26902:8"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <item>Inſtructions for the <hi>Oſtringer</hi> to obſerue. p. <hi>5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>He that giues not due attendance, ſhall neuer attaine to perfect knowledge. ibid:</item>
               <item>A yong man to lye long in bed, and be ſlothfull, is a vice deteſtable. ibid.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. IIII.</head>
               <item>Of the difference in the manner of flying of the <hi>Goſhawke,</hi> compared with the other, which the <hi>Oſtringer</hi> ought to obſerue. p. <hi>6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Difference in their flight. ibid.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <item>Of the nature of the <hi>Goſhawke</hi> compared with the <hi>Lanner</hi> for her ſoundneſſe and long laſting, the which dependeth vpon the well ordering and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerning of the Keeper. p <hi>7</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Shee is euer free of diuers infirmities that other <hi>Hawkes</hi> are ſubiect vnto. ibid.</item>
               <item>The power of her naturall heate. p. <hi>8</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Care in the Keeper preſerueth life. ibid:</item>
               <item>The nature of the <hi>Goſhawke. 9</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The gentle diſpoſition of the <hi>Lanner.</hi> ibid.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <item>Of the skilfull <hi>Oſtringer,</hi> and how he may through negligence as ſoone deſtroy and kill his <hi>Hawke,</hi> as one of more ſlender iudgement. p. <hi>10</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The fruits of careleſneſſe in the skilfull Keeper. ibid.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <item>Inſtructions for the yong man from the Mew p. <hi>11</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the Mew. ibid.</item>
               <item>Neceſſarie inſtructions. p. <hi>12</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:26902:8"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <item>Of the <hi>Goſhawke</hi> taken from the cage, with other obſeruations for the young man. p. <hi>13.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If they reſt long on the cage there will be great dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage in the ſodaine dealing with her. ibid.</item>
               <item>Inſtructions for the young man. p. <hi>15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of caſting. p. <hi>16</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The nature of the ſtomacke. p. <hi>16</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The caſting. p. <hi>17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Diſorder in the giuer of caſting. p. <hi>18</hi>
               </item>
               <item>More of caſting. p. <hi>13</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The effects of woollen caſting. p. <hi>19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The naturall caſting. p. <hi>20</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of bloudy meate giuen to flying <hi>Hawkes.</hi> p. <hi>21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The effects of groſſe feeding. p. <hi>21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Difference betweene the <hi>Hawke</hi> in the Mewe, and the other that is flying. p. <hi>21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Order in the inſeaming. p. <hi>22.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What ſhe gets by the labour of the body, and vſe of her wings and thriues beſt with her. p. <hi>22</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Franke feede with reſt breeds imperfection and lets the ſtomacke. p. <hi>22</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the ſtomacke. p. <hi>23</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the Couart. p. <hi>23</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The inconuenience of long faſting. p. <hi>23</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That your <hi>Hawke</hi> be not kept faſting too long for her flying. p. <hi>24</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of colde meate. p. <hi>24</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The benefit of good meate. p. <hi>24</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of ſetting your <hi>Hawke</hi> downe to reſt. p. <hi>25</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of taking her vp againe. p. <hi>25</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26902:9"/>The patience of the <hi>Oſtringer</hi> toward his <hi>Hauk. 26</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An order to be vſed at the firſt reclaiming. p. <hi>26</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An obſeruation at the firſt entrance. p. <hi>27</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The fruits of an imperfect ſtomacke. p. <hi>27</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <item>Of a <hi>Hawke</hi> that will not endure or abide the ſight of the hood. p. <hi>28</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An error in the keeper. p. <hi>28</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <item>To make the the <hi>Goſhawke</hi> gentle, and to loue the hood, that hath with ill vſage beene beaten cut of loue withall before. p. <hi>30</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An order to be obſerued. p. <hi>30</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <item>To reclaime the <hi>Hawke</hi> from the cage. p. <hi>33</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An order to be obſerued. p. <hi>34</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A good caueat. p. <hi>35</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Obſerue the nature of the <hi>Hawke.</hi> p. <hi>36</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Haue care of her stomacke. p. <hi>37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Marke well how ſhe ought to be called. ibid.</item>
               <item>Ouer ſight in the keeper. ibid.</item>
               <item>The fruits of haſtineſſe. p. <hi>38</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of vaineglory. ibid.</item>
               <item>The low and poore <hi>Hawke</hi> is euermore ſubiect to infirmitie. ibid.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <item>How and in what manner the <hi>Goſhawke</hi> ought to be called looſe, and taught to draw, and in what places for the better auoyding of ſuch inconuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as ſhe is ſubiect vnto. p. <hi>40</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The ſpoyle of the <hi>Hawke.</hi> p. <hi>41</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26902:9"/>Flying to a towne. ibid.</item>
               <item>An order to be obſerued at firſt teaching to draw. ib.</item>
               <item>Why you ought not to call her aloud. p. <hi>42</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
               <item>To make loue and vnity between the <hi>Oſtringer</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, his <hi>Hawke</hi> and his <hi>Spaniels,</hi> which is a ſpeciall thing to be obſerued. p. <hi>43</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The breeding loue between the <hi>Hawke</hi> and the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niels,</hi> p <hi>44</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To know when your <hi>Hawke</hi> is ready to flye. p <hi>45</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. XIIII.</head>
               <item>How you ſhall firſt enter your <hi>Hawke,</hi> and teach her flye to the field, and to order and manage her there during that ſeaſon. p. <hi>46</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the <hi>Spaniels.</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>Of the buſhe. p. <hi>47</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Some words of cuſtome ibid.</item>
               <item>Of the Partridge. ibid.</item>
               <item>An obſeruation. p. <hi>48</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An order to be obſerued. p. <hi>49</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A neceſſary example. p. <hi>50</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An ill quality to fall on the ground. p. <hi>53</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to amend the fault. ibid.</item>
               <item>A great error. p. <hi>54</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A good condition. p. <hi>55</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Faults in the <hi>Eyas Hawke.</hi> p. <hi>56</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the <hi>Ramage Hawke.</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>A neceſſary example. ibid.</item>
               <item>An inconuenience belonging to the <hi>Hawke</hi> that will not take the hood. p. <hi>57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Often bating at Partridges ſprung to other <hi>Hawks</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26902:10"/>
diſcomforteth and diſcourageth the <hi>Hawke.</hi> p. <hi>59</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of <hi>Hawkes</hi> that haue true mettle. p. <hi>66</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. XV.</head>
               <item>How to enter the <hi>Goſhawke</hi> to the Couart. pag. <hi>61</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To teach the <hi>Goſhawke</hi> flye to the Couart. ibid.</item>
               <item>Euery one not fit to keepe the <hi>Goſhawke.</hi> p. <hi>62</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The man cannot follow by view to ſerue the <hi>Hawke.</hi> p. <hi>63</hi>
               </item>
               <item>It is the nature of a <hi>Hawke</hi> to haue her prey in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate. p. <hi>64</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the <hi>Hawke</hi> and the Pheaſant. p. <hi>65</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the <hi>Hawke</hi> and the <hi>Spaniels:</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>The time to enter a <hi>Hawke.</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>To beware of the <hi>Spaniels.</hi> p. <hi>66</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Shewing of true loue. ibid.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hawkes</hi> muſt haue no diſcouragement at their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering. ibid.</item>
               <item>A good obſeruation for young men. ibid.</item>
               <item>A great error or ouerſight. p. <hi>67</hi>
               </item>
               <item>More faults. p. <hi>68</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Why Dogs are ſent before. p. <hi>69</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Halter fitteſt for theeues. ibid.</item>
               <item>A good obſeruation. ibid.</item>
               <item>The <hi>Spaniels</hi> muſt know what they hunt for. p. <hi>70</hi>
               </item>
               <item>There muſt be a continuance of carefull vſage. p. <hi>71</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hawkes</hi> angry, and her keeper not wel pleaſed. ib.</item>
               <item>To embolden the <hi>Hawke,</hi> and make her take the Pheaſant from the pearche with courage. p. <hi>72</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To keepe dogs in awe. ibid.</item>
               <item>To beware of ſtrange dogs. p. <hi>73</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A great inconuenience. p. <hi>74</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26902:10"/>An excellent diſh. ibid.</item>
               <item>Of entring to the Cocke. ibid.</item>
               <item>To ſeeke out the nature of the <hi>Hawke.</hi> p. <hi>75</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of great indiſcretion. ibid.</item>
               <item>A daſtard <hi>Hawke</hi> will kill the hen Pheſant. ibid.</item>
               <item>Whats worthy commendations. p <hi>76</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. XVI.</head>
               <item>A note worthy of obſeruation for the imboldning of any <hi>Hawke</hi> that hath beene rebuked or diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the Spaniels. p. <hi>77</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An order perfectly to imbolden her. p. <hi>78</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. XVII.</head>
               <item>Of the <hi>Haggart Goſhawke</hi> in particular. p. <hi>80</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the <hi>Haggart.</hi> p. <hi>81</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Crowes, Kites, and other ſuch vermine. p. <hi>83</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Great inconuenience. ibid.</item>
               <item>A <hi>Hawke</hi> muſt be alwaies pleaſed from the hand. <hi>85</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the thicke Couart. ibid.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. XVIII.</head>
               <item>That the <hi>Hawke</hi> being well entred, and in loue with the Partridge, ought not to be flone to the Couart at all. p. <hi>86</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of a toling and tempting bird. p. <hi>87</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the Pheſant. ibid.</item>
               <item>The true nature of the <hi>Hawke.</hi> p. <hi>88.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. XIX.</head>
               <item>To teach the <hi>Goſhawke</hi> to flye to the wild Ducke or Mallard that frequents the ponds or priuate pits, which is a good ſport, and a good prey when it is taken. p. <hi>89</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The nature of the Fowle. <hi>90</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26902:11"/>Spurs to pricke the <hi>Hawke</hi> forward: p. <hi>91</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. XX.</head>
               <item>To flye to the wilde Gooſe or Hearne, to the Rooke, the Mew or any other ſuch ſhort flight; which are to be kild at the ſudden ſound by the policie of the <hi>Hawke</hi> that is not ſwift of her wing to take them otherwiſe. p. <hi>93</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>Hawkes</hi> loue. p. <hi>94</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An addition and example. ibid.</item>
               <item>Of the trayne. <hi>96</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A good condition. p. <hi>97</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. XXI.</head>
               <item>Of the <hi>Sparrow-hawke.</hi> p. <hi>99</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. XXII:</head>
               <item>Of the <hi>Lanner</hi> and <hi>Lanneret.</hi> p. <hi>102</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. XXIII.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the</hi> Haggart Lanner. <hi>p.</hi> 104</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. XXIIII.</head>
               <item>Of the <hi>Ramage Lanner</hi> to the field. p. <hi>106</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. XXV.</head>
               <item>Of the <hi>Ramage Lanner</hi> for the Riuer. p. <hi>111</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The nouice or young <hi>Hawke.</hi> p. <hi>113</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Neyther too much at one time, nor too little at at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. p. <hi>116</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. XXVI.</head>
               <item>Of the <hi>Ramage Lanneret</hi> eyther to the Riuer or Field. p. <hi>118</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the Partridge: p. <hi>119</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. XXVII:</head>
               <item>Of the <hi>Eyas Lanner</hi> or <hi>Lanneret.</hi> p. <hi>121</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of <hi>Haggart</hi> or <hi>Ramage Hawkes.</hi> p. <hi>122</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:26902:11"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXVIII.</head>
               <item>Of the cold in the head, or the <hi>Rye.</hi> p. <hi>129</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. XXIX.</head>
               <item>For the <hi>Rye,</hi> or ſtuffing in the head. p. <hi>132</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. XXX.</head>
               <item>Of the <hi>Craye.</hi> p. <hi>134</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. XXXI.</head>
               <item>Of the <hi>Eye.</hi> p. <hi>139</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. XXXII.</head>
               <item>A medicine for the eye that ſhall haue any hurt by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, or otherwiſe be growne vpon it. p. <hi>140</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. XXXIII.</head>
               <item>Of the <hi>Hobby</hi> and the <hi>Marlion.</hi> p. <hi>141</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:26902:12"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:26902:12"/>
            <head>LATHAMS new, and ſecond Booke of FALCONRY.</head>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>GO SHAWKE.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the <hi>Goſhawke</hi> compared with other <hi>Fowles</hi> of the aire, as they are vnreclaimed and wilde; and of the awe and fearefulneſſe they haue of man aboue all other creatures.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Any an Oſteringer accounts that ſo ſoone as he hath reclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med his <hi>Hawke,</hi> taught her to draw and come againe to his fiſt, that euen ſo ſoone he may preſume and bee bold to goe with her to the field or couert, and make her doe his will; but it is not ſo. And he, whatſoeuer he
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:26902:13"/>
be that ſo thinketh, ſhall be deceiued in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation: for I haue knowne my ſelfe diuers and ſundrie of the beſt mettelled <hi>Haukes,</hi> with that ſlight and and ſimple conceit to haue beene vtterly ſpoiled, euen quickly, and for euer bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten out of loue with their Keeper, his Spaniels, and the game hee hath flone and entered them firſt vnto; which ſhall hereafter more plainely appeare, and be proued vnto you.</p>
               <p>Firſt, you are to vnderſtand, that all <hi>Haukes</hi> whatſoeuer in their owne nature and kinde, doe of all other creatures, that God hath made and framed to perfection, moſt dread and feare the man. As for example, do but obſerue the wilde <hi>Hauke,</hi> or other <hi>Fowles</hi> that are bred in ſtrange or forren Countries, where as few or no people be; let thoſe birds that comes at paſſage into theſe parts or other places, and in their owne deſires being moued thereunto, doe offer to fall or light whereas diuers and ſundrie ſorts of beaſtes or cattell be, yet without much timeritie or feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, they will very often and amongſt them all euen make their ſtay: on the contrary part, whenſoeuer they doe but fixe their eyes on one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s very proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they wil not abide; no, they will hardly by any art, with ſtale annexed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, be drawne or tempted to ſtoope within his view: which ſtrange behauiour of theirs doth manifeſtly proue, and ſhew how timerous and dreadfull they be of him. Therefore if he doe couet to haue, or will haue one or any of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:26902:13"/>
thoſe kinde of wilde <hi>Creatures</hi> to be at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and familiar with him, that by nature and kinde are altogether ſhye and fearefull of him; he muſt firſt when he hath them, draw and win them by his continuall louing and curteous be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour towards them, in his art and outward manner of dealing with them. For of all <hi>Hawkes</hi> in the world (the <hi>Goſhawke</hi>) as ſhee is a ſtately and braue bird to behold; ſo is ſhee alſo as coy, nice, and curious to be handled and dealt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. And will as ſoone obſerue and vnkindly except againſt any rough or harſh behauiour from the man, towards her<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> on the contrarie, being artificially and kindly reclamed and vſed, ſhee will be as louing and fond of her Keeper, as any other <hi>Hawke</hi> whatſoeuer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the <hi>Spaniel,</hi> and the ſocietie there ought to bee betweene the man, the <hi>Hawke,</hi> and himſelfe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Spanyel</hi> is ſo kind a creature, that of all other,<note place="margin">Of the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niell.</note> the man doth moſt reſpect &amp; chuſe to attend &amp; wait vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him euery where, as well at home in his chamber, as at his table &amp; trencher. And further, for his delight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in al other places, ſo wel hee doth accept &amp; account of his company: &amp; truly no maruell why; but that he ſhould be of him ſo well eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:26902:14"/>
and delighted in. For it hath been affirmed of him for veritie, that if in the night-time there hath beene or ſhould bee, any euill thing neere vnto his maſter, whom hee doth waite on, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though hee is not bound or tied vnto him, but might therefore take to his feete and runne quite from him, yet otherwiſe he will be ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding fond in his loue towards him, as that in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtead of that, he will ſtay ſtill with him, and with lamentable mone and whining, will euen creepe and crawle about his legs to giue him warning. Furthermore, if in the day-time any euill fall through tempeſt of thunder, lightning, or any other euill blaſt, the poore louing <hi>Spanyel</hi> is ſure of it to taſte, to ſet his maſter free. And therefore of all other creatures, I hold him in his owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and kindly loue, to bee moſt neare familiar and in true ſubiection with the man, euer deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to be with him, and neuer willing to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, or out of the way from him, but ſtill watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and diligent to doe him ſeruice. So likewiſe, of all other things, the <hi>Hawke</hi> in her owne incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation doth as much feare, and is terrified at the ſight of him, hee being one ſo neere as in conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual ſociety or company keeping with the man. Wherefore it behoueth euery one that loueth and deſireth to keepe the <hi>Goſhawke,</hi> to be ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, that by his arte and beſt indeuour, hee doe frame and faſhion, as it were, a league of loue and familiar vnitie, betweene them, I meane the <hi>Man,</hi> the <hi>Hawke,</hi> and the <hi>Spanyel;</hi> the which to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:26902:14"/>
accompliſh and bring to perfection, I will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my owne iudgement and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding hereafter ſhew you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Inſtructions for the <hi>Oſteringer</hi> to obſerue.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Would haue you vnderſtand, that as many a <hi>Falconer</hi> paſſeth ouer the time he hath with his <hi>Hawke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hee that giues not due atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, ſhall neuer attain to perfect knowledge.</note> &amp; for want of true knowledge &amp; vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, neuer finds out that goodnes in her, which in her own nature &amp; diſpoſition ſhe is able to performe. So alſo oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the <hi>Oſteringer</hi> with his <hi>Goſhawk</hi> doth ſpend his time in vaine, for want of the like knowledge &amp; perfect experience in his arte;<note place="margin">For a yong man to lye long in bed, and be ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, is a vice dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable.</note> for there is very few of that kinde, but through skill and painfull practiſe may be made good: if neither for <hi>Feſant</hi> nor <hi>Partridge,</hi> the which are moſt mens vſuall delights, yet for ſome other thing, whereby her Keeper may bee pleaſed, and ſhee her ſelfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue a due reward. For all of them, as they are wilde and vnreclaimed, are able ſufficiently to ſhift for themſelues, and kill ſundrie kindes of prey to ſuſtaine their owne wants withall. If that be ſo, wherefore then ſhould not a skilfull Keeper, by his arte, paines and diſcretion, cauſe any of them to doe the like for him?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:26902:15"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> Of the difference in the manner of flying of the <hi>Goſhawke,</hi> compared with the other, which the <hi>Oſteringer</hi> ought to obſerue.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>GO SHAWKE.</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Difference in their flight.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere is further to be noted, that as in the obſeruation of euery <hi>Falconer,</hi> there is much difference in the maner of flying of their long winged <hi>Hawkes</hi> to be marked: ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is there by the <hi>Ostringer</hi> with his ſhortwinged <hi>Hawke,</hi> as great a matter to bee obſerued: for as ſome <hi>Falcon</hi> or lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g winged <hi>Hawke</hi> being flone to the field, is as it were, vnable to ouertake the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridge</hi> at the firſt flight on forhead, but is taught by nature, and alſo enforced further by nurture, to clime and mount aloft vpon the marke, for her better aduantage, and after that manner kill it at the downe come: ſo on the contrary there is ſome others, that onely truſteth to their ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:26902:15"/>
to prey at their will and pleaſures on what they liſteth. Likewiſe for the ſhort-winged <hi>Hawkes,</hi> they are as much different in their kind; for the ſwift and faſt flying <hi>Hawke</hi> doth maſter her prey, when ſhee is diſpoſed, and forceth it to yeeld through the ſwiftnes of her main wings: contrariwiſe, the flower flying <hi>Hawke</hi> or ſlugge doth winne what ſhee gets moſt by her pollicie, wherein being reclaimed, ſhee ought to bee taught &amp; furthered by the induſtry &amp; art of her Keeper.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of the nature of the <hi>Goſhawke</hi> compared with the <hi>Lanner,</hi> for her ſoundneſſe and long la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting; the which dependeth vpon the well ordering and gouerning of her Keeper.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Goſhawk</hi> is a <hi>Hawk</hi> of a hot nature,<note place="margin">She is euer free of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities that other Hawkes be ſubiect vnto.</note> &amp; ſtronger co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitution the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any other <hi>Hawke</hi> that I my ſelf haue knowne, of what kind ſoeuer: for in my obſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe is ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, or not at al, ſubiect to be liuer ſhot, neither euer to haue the fella<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders, both which infirmities are very rife &amp; familiar with our other ordinary <hi>Hawkes,</hi> and alſo proceeds from much coldnes, the one of the liuer, the other of the ſtomacke; from colde, but of heate from colde: becauſe when the <hi>Hawke</hi> is once liuerſhot, at that time
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:26902:16"/>
the liuer is both cold and rotten; which for the moſt part, firſt doth proceed of ſome violent heate taken by extraordinary meanes and euill vſage; and therefore, I ſay, from immediate and preſent cold, and of foretaken or former heate. Alſo, when ſhee is in the meaneſt and pooreſt eſtate of her body, what meate ſoeuer paſſeth thorow her, is euer conuerted and turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a liquid and thin ſubſtance; which ſheweth plainely the power of her naturall heate and ſtrength of body,<note place="margin">The power of her natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall heate.</note> ſo long as life remaineth in her.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Lanner</hi> and <hi>Lanneret</hi> are accounted hard <hi>Hawkes,</hi> &amp; the very hardieſt of any kind that are ordinary, or in common vſe amongſt vs at this preſent time: for whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſoeuer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendations ſhal be by many men giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the <hi>Goſhawke</hi> or <hi>Tarcel</hi> for their long laſting, or liuing; they will ſimply ſay they bee as hard as the <hi>Lanner.</hi> But that ought not to bee ſo affirmed or beleeued, but with ſome exception, as touching the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and skill of their Keeper,<note place="margin">Care in the Keeper pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth life.</note> to be performed towards them in good rule and order, at al times fitting for them; and then I will ioyne with them, and ſay indeed, they bee ſound <hi>Hawkes,</hi> and as ſound and hard of ward as the <hi>Lanner;</hi> for you are to vnderſtand thus much of her natural inclination, which is, that ſhee is a <hi>Hawke</hi> full of ſtoutneſſe and courage, and will not incline her ſelfe, neither be forced to be conformable in any reaſonable &amp; meane temper vnto her Keepers
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:26902:16"/>
will, in the time of her pride and fulneſſe; when as ſhee ought by labour and practiſe, to bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeamed and made readie for his purpoſe, but is and will be frowardly diſpoſed,<note place="margin">The nature of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hawke.</note> and prone to vnrulineſſe and extreame bating in that ſeaſon; which is the cauſe generally that one of them requireth more labour and attendance of her Keeper, then any other <hi>Hawke</hi> whatſoeuer of contrarie kinde: neuertheleſſe, oftten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times through theſe extreames, and in thoſe times, they doe haſte and ſhorten their owne dayes.</p>
               <p>Contrariwiſe, as touching the <hi>Lanner,</hi> for the moſt part ſhee is as meeke and gently diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,<note place="margin">The gentle diſpoſition of the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</note> and ſeldome or neuer will of her owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, or through other prouocation bee made to bate, or forced to any extraordinarie vnruli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe during the time of her inſeaming; but will wholly diſpoſe her ſelfe to quietneſſe, and endure all things continually with patience; which is the onely cauſe, and wherefore thoſe kinde of <hi>Hawkes</hi> by all reaſon muſt needs ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſt the other.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:26902:17"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of the skilfull <hi>Oſtringer,</hi> and how he may through his negligence as ſoone deſtroy and kill his <hi>Hawke,</hi> as one of more ſlender iudgement.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere is the difference in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall kinds, and it reſteth to bee confirmed, as I haue ſaid before; by the skill; and not onely that, but alſo the care and diligence of their Keeper: for if he be neuer ſo good a <hi>Faulconer</hi> or <hi>Oſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,</hi> yet may be through negligence and muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble affections, oft-times ſuffer the ſoundeſt and hardieſt <hi>Hawke</hi> to decay and periſh for want of due attendance.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The fruits of careleſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the skilful Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</note>For I haue my ſelfe beene acquainted with ſome ſpeciall <hi>Falconers,</hi> whom, if I were diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, I could name; who, for their skill and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience in their art, haue beene perfectly able firſt to reclaime, inſeame, and make their <hi>Hawkes</hi> to flye; and after with great skill and iudgement to order and manage them in their flights du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that ſeaſon: but afterwards hauing finiſhed and concluded the ſame, being returned to their home, would there ſet them downe, and as it were, vtterly diſclaiming all former acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance had with them, would there let them
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:26902:17"/>
ſometimes ſitte, and other ſometimes hang by the heeles, betaking themſelues for that day or night wholly, to Tables, Cards, Tobacco, or ſome other ſuch vaine delights, whereby and through which cauſe they haue wanted their dues, their dayes haue beene ſhortened, and their liues euen wilfully haſted on to an end.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Inſtructions for the yong man from the Mewe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is meete the yong man that wants experience ſhould haue ſuch light and vnderſtanding ſhewed him by rules and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as that in his firſt leſſon he may bee taught to diſcerne and know what difference there ought to bee in the dyet and manner of feeding, with the order belonging to his <hi>Hawke</hi> in her flying time, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo when ſhee is in the Mew, and during the time of her being there.</p>
               <p>Therefore, if ſhee be a <hi>Hawke</hi> that hath beene formerly ſtone, and is to be taken from thence,<note place="margin">The Mew.</note> it is like ſhee will bee fat and full in the higheſt degree with reſt and francke feeding; and there would be great danger in the ſudden drawing of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:26902:18"/>
her, and it is vnuſuall with men of any iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſo to doe: wherefore it is neceſſarie that ſhee bee fed in the Mew twice euery day, with cleane dreſt and waſht meat, for the ſpace of ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen or twenty daies before the intended time of her drawing, to the end ſhee may be at that time well inſeamed of her bodie,<note place="margin">Neceſſary inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</note> and haue ſcoured forth of her pannell and guts ſuch glot and fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, with other droſſie ſubſtance, that was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendred and harboured there; by means wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſhee will be perfectly freed from any danger that otherwiſe might haue happened afterward vnto her, through her bating or other forcible motion of bodie, as ſtrugling, ſtriuing, or ſuch like at her drawing, or other times. Then will it be good time to take her from the Mew, when as you muſt haue a rufter hood in a readineſſe very fit for her; from which time forwards ſhe muſt be continually fed on the fiſt, after the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner formerly preſcribed; alſo to haue caſting e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery night duely beſtowed on her.</p>
               <p>This courſe, with continual cariage on horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backe and on foote, muſt bee taken with her in her rufter hood ſome eight or ten dayes longer, and then take if off when you ſhall finde her to be well reclaimed and inſeamed, and free from all danger, and ready to be called: and with dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and paines therein, the next weeke will be as ready to flye; and after two or three flights at her firſt entering, may be put euen to hard fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſhee will receiue no harme thereby, ſhe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:26902:18"/>
will be ſo perfectly inſeamed; whereas otherwiſe with more haſte ſhee may ſurfet on heat, or with hard and ſhort feed, loſe her fleſh, and ſo be ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for two whole yeares.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <figure>
                     <head>GO SHAWKE.</head>
                  </figure>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Of the <hi>Goſhawke</hi> taken from the Cage, with other obſeruations for the yong man.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F ſhee be newly taken from the Cage,<note place="margin">If ſhee reſt long in the cage, there will be great danger in the ſodaine dealing with her,</note> or thoſe that fetches them from for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain and ſtrange Countries, and takes no more care in their trauell and cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, but only to diſpoſe and deliuer them aliue heere amongſt vs, for their owne benefite and commodities; There is very few or none of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:26902:19"/>
thoſe <hi>Hawkes</hi> euer ſo ouerfraught with fatte or fulneſſe of bodie, whereby ſhe may take harme with any reaſonable or ordinary bating, or ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring on the fiſt, for that ſhee hath beene former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and vſually acquainted with the ſame in her long and reſtleſſe iourney: wherefore you need not doubt or feare, but euen ſo ſoone as your leiſure will permit, after you haue her, to begin to practiſe and deale with her, and by your arte and beſt endeauour, together with your labour to man and reclaime her after the maner as ſhall be ſhewed hereafter; only noting and obſeruing by the way theſe things. Firſt, you are to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime and make a wilde <hi>Hawke</hi> and a bird of the ayre, that onely feares you, to become lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and gentle vnto you, and alſo, as it were, to be ſociable and familiar with you. Likewiſe ſhe being by vnskilfull and careleſſe former bad v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, with vnnaturall dyet and groſſe feeding, ſuffocated and filled full of vncleaneneſſe and imperfection; you are through your skill and painefull practiſe, to purge and cleanſe her of thoſe groſſe and ſuperfluous humors, and make her a perfect <hi>Hawke,</hi> and readie with fitneſſe to be reclaimed, and framed for what purpoſe ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you intend to make her for.</p>
               <p>And that theſe things may well bee accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed and brought to perfection without any artificiall medicine or ſcouring: you ſhall haue the certaine and ſure way deliuered vnto you by rule and inſtruction: yet I know there bee
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:26902:19"/>
many men otherwiſe affected, and will hardly be perſwaded to be thereto conceited. But let them be well aduiſed, for I ſpeake not by heare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay or imagination, or from any other printed tradition, but by my owne experience and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued concluſion, as ſhall appeare hereafter; yet I may imagine I ſhould not need to vſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny words for perſwaſion, knowing that many experienced <hi>Oſtringers</hi> vnderſtands the ſame: and for my owne part I can iuſtly affirme that I haue kept ſome few of the kinde, whereof one of them liued with me aboue a doſen yeare, and neuer had, during that time, any kind of phyſick giuen vnto her; and therefore ſo farre, as out of my owne knowledge I may, I do wiſh the yong man, that theſe following directions may be his direct and ſetled courſe in the reclaiming, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaming, and keeping his <hi>Hawke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Vſe onely a right and good order in her dyet,<note place="margin">Inſtructions for the yong man.</note> with ſweete meate at all times cleane dreſſed, and reaſonably waſhed, or according as he ſhall find her of gentle or ſtubborne nature; &amp; alſo a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable quantitie to bee giuen vnto her ſo often as hereafter he ſhall be further inſtructed: like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with caſting duely beſtowed on her, if he findes her to be ſound, and to like of caſting of woollen, then let her haue it; but otherwiſe let it be ſuch as agreeth beſt with her owne nature; for there be many right ſound <hi>Hawkes</hi> of that kinde, that will on euery great gorge, through the long keeping of ſuch woollen caſtings, much
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:26902:20"/>
diſtaſte them; the hot ſtench and ſauour of them wil be ſo noyſome and diſagreeing with the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, that workes and ſtriues for the time to diſgeſt what it receiues into it,<note place="margin">The nature of the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke.</note> vntill it findes, as it were, a certaine contending or vnnatural wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king againſt it ſelfe; &amp; being in nature va<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quiſhed and ouercome by the ſame, it is conſtrained to yeeld and free it cleerely of it, by reſtoring or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning it backe to him that gaue it.</p>
               <p>And to preuent this loathing, or diſlike of this kinde of caſting, or any euill that might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der or grow therby: I haue many yeares paſt left off to giue any of them to my <hi>Hawke</hi> at the night-time, neither at any time to keepe within her bodie aboue one houre, or two at the moſt, by my good will. Which courſe I haue found to be very agreeable with any <hi>Hawke</hi> in health, or in meane eſtate, and to preuaile as much with her, in ſcouring or clenſing the place that har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours or containes it, of all ſuperfluous matter therein contained, to the deſired wiſh or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment of the beholder: for whoſe further ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, I will heere briefely make it plaine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you.</p>
               <p>If you haue read ouer my other booke of <hi>Falconrie,</hi> you may remember, or if you do reade it, there you ſhall finde, that I haue written and diſcourſed of Caſtings ſufficiently; and ſhewed the yong <hi>Falconer,</hi> how hee may at the firſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of his <hi>Hawke,</hi> eyther make her therein to loue her caſting euer after; or otherwiſe for want
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:26902:20"/>
of knowledge cauſe her euerlaſtingly to hate the ſame, or at leaſt alwayes to bee nice and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to take it; which is one moſt vile condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and doth condemne the Keeper,<note place="margin">The caſting</note> either in his iudgement or carefulneſſe, or both; for the beſt or skilfulleſt that is cannot gouerne ſuch an <hi>Hawke</hi> as ſhee ought to bee. And becauſe I haue writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo largly before, I wil now briefly let you vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that at the firſt reclaiming &amp; making, is the time to teach her, when as with good meat cleane dreſſed and waſhed, and reaſonable gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the ſame, with the like time adioyned, you muſt get her a good ſtomacke before you prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer her one caſting, and then ſhee will not bee nice or curious to take it; alwayes being minde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that it be no more in quantitie, but that ſhe may well and eaſily ſwallow; and then when ſhe hath ſo done, preſently put on her hood, and ſuddenly giue her one bitte or two of meate to pleaſe her withall; then make a little ſtay, vntill you perceiue aſſuredly that ſhee hath put it downe into her pannell; which being perceiued put on her hood againe, and giue her a reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſupper: and this courſe it is fit ſhould be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with her continually, as after the receit of her caſting, as you haue heard, to let her ſit in her hood vntill ſhee hath put it into her pannell, and you ſhall ſee it will not be long before ſhee will vnderſtand what ſhee ſhould doe; and in all loue vnto it, will haſten without any niceneſſe to take it euen of it ſelfe, expecting a preſent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:26902:21"/>
after ſhee hath receiued it; alſo otherwiſe it is very neceſſary to hold this courſe. For I haue ſeene my ſelfe ſome men, that before their caſting were any whit downe their <hi>Hawkes</hi> throate,<note place="margin">Diſorder in the giuer of caſting.</note> would follow her ſo haſtily with meat, that ſhee hath beene almoſt choaked: but how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, it will oftentimes very much moleſt her in her putting ouer and imbowelling; the which you way perceiue by her often writhing, and great trouble in trauerſing with her necke and whole body.</p>
               <p>On theſe conſiderations, after my <hi>Hawke</hi> is well in ſeamed, and in flying, I faile not, ſo neere as I can, to giue her plumage euery night when I feed her vp: contrariwiſe, when ſhee doth reſt from her labour, then I feede her very cleane without any caſting at all, and ſo doe ſet her vp to reſt:<note place="margin">Of caſting.</note> then doe I cut and faſhion a caſting of woollen to my liking, and lay it in faire water all night, and the next morning doe riſe very ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and doe offer her the ſame, well ſoaked, coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and waſhed; the which ſhee will not refuſe to take willingly, ſitting ſtill on her pearch, being formerly wonted and accuſtomed vnto it, and will put it downe into her pannell; and within ſome houre, or thereabouts, when her ſtomack hath wrought vpon it, and findes little or no commoditie gained therby, then doth her emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe and eager appetite to her breakfaſt, natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally prouoke her by caſting to make her readie to prepare her ſelfe for the ſame: at which time,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:26902:21"/>
for your further experience, you may behold what a faire and delicate caſting it will be, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ill ſigne or ſhew in it; which otherwiſe would haue appeared, by the length of time continued.</p>
               <p>Thus in my owne obſeruation I haue gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that this kinde of caſting is not fit to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vſually at the night time vnto the ſoundeſt <hi>Hawke</hi> of this kinde, eſpecially with any ſtore of meate that may giue cauſe vnto her to keepe it long: for triall whereof, you ſhall perceiue in the morning that it hath vexed her in her ſtomacke, and hindered her digeſtion, and that ſhee hath beene wearie of it with detaining it ſo long. For triall whereof, oft-times it forceth her to caſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her due houre, or that ſhee hath perfectly indued her ſupper,<note place="margin">The effects of woollen caſting.</note> which will appeare in the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of it, that will be of a blacke burnt or taw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, and withall clammie, with muddie and bloudie water in it very often, euen in the ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt <hi>Hawke</hi> that is.</p>
               <p>Thus doe I leaue it to your conſiderations, whether it can be fit or meete to be giuen vnto a ſickly or craſie <hi>Hawke,</hi> or no, when the ſoundeſt that is cannot well nor alwaies brooke it. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, by my aduice, if any man will needs giue it at the night, let it be but with ſmal ſtore of meat, and alſo let her haue ſome plumage with it. There be ſome men that vſe to giue ſtones with ſaliendine, and caſtings of haſſell, that will ſwell dangerouſly, and grow too bigge without great
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:26902:22"/>
care be had in the vnderſizing of it; the which many are much ouerſeene in, and oftentimes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſtraine their <hi>Hawkes</hi> with too great caſtings of ſuch kinde, as will not with her inward and naturall working be ſo faſhioned and mollified, as that ſhe may caſt it again with any reaſonable eaſines, or without much preiudice to herſelfe.</p>
               <p>Alſo others doe vſe to giue quilles and ſuch like vnto theſe kind of <hi>Hawkes,</hi> both in their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaming and flying time: but for my owne part I ioyne not with them in the like opinion, but rather doe eſteeme of them as vaine and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous imaginations, and conceits proceeding from mutable and vnconſtant affections, then from any effects of certentie or probable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions: only this hath been mine own courſe, when I haue found my <hi>Hawke</hi> any whit to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſte or diſlike of ſuch kinde of vnnaturall cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton caſtings, I ſodainely left them, and did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take my ſelfe to Iukes, and ſometimes to Hares or Conies feete, the bones and wooll well bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken together; the which I neuer found to diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree any whit with her,<note place="margin">The natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall caſting is beſt.</note> but alwayes hath wrought to good purpoſe, and the like effects in her. And whoſoeuer he be that is cleanely in his manner of dyet or feeding, and for the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie, with the carefull ordering of the ſame, moſt aſſuredly ſhall neuer haue any occaſion to vſe ſuch kinde of extraordinary courſes. Yet I know there bee many men that would haue their <hi>Hawkes</hi> to flie well, and bee at their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:26902:22"/>
with groſſe and bloudie meate giuen and continued vnto them,<note place="margin">Of bloudy meate giuen to ſtring Hawkes.</note> euen as if they were ſtill in the Mew; and they will not through any coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell bee aduiſed from that courſe, although they plainly perceiue what inconuenience belongeth vnto it: as firſt, they wil ſeeme and make ſhew to be, as it were, blind &amp; careleſſe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhould be moſt careful &amp; watchful to ſee &amp; fly for their own reward, &amp; content of their keeper: alſo they wil loyter &amp; ſit drowſily behind, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhold be moſt diligent to attend &amp; draw after the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">The effects of groſſe feeding.</note> nay although they fal to raling or ſoring quite away from them, yet they will be ſo ſhallow witted or otherwiſe ſelfe-wil conceited, as either they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not or will not iudge of the true cauſe of their idlenes or diſobedience towards them, which is nothing but the imperfectneſſe of the ſtomack, that is grown ſo cold, &amp; glotted with foule feed vnwaſht, &amp; great gorges. I do not deny, but that hot and bloudy meat is neceſſary &amp; good, if he that giues it knows when it is fit to beſtow it, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe it auaileth nothing towards the effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al working of his deſire. For example, take the wilde <hi>Hawke</hi> from the Cage,<note place="margin">Difference betweene the Hawke in the Mew and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that is flying.</note> or otherwiſe from the Mew the <hi>Hawke</hi> that hath beene flone, and continue your former wonted manner of fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with bloudie meate vnto her, although diuiding the ſame with your beſt diſcretion, and taking away the fatte and groſſeſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from it; alſo to plye her with caſting, carriage, and all the paines with watching, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:26902:23"/>
whatſoeuer elſe belonging, vntill you haue made her ſo familiar and gentle, as you can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe or deſire, in the houſe in company, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in hold. Yet neuertheleſſe, if you omit, and be ſlacke to take the bloud away with well waſhing, you ſhall be new to ſeeke; for your la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour is all in vaine, and ſhee will not bee reclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med or forced to be ſubiect to your will, but wil continue in a manner towards you both wilde and ramage ſtill, whenſoeuer you ſhall croſſe her looſe abroad: and therefore I would haue to vnderſtand,<note place="margin">Order in the inſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</note> that the vnreclaimed and vnclean <hi>Hawke,</hi> of this kind or any other, ought to bee reclaimed, inſeamed, and made to flye, with good meate cleane dreſſed and waſhed, and for theſe <hi>Hawkes,</hi> the water dryed out againe with a faire cloath, and a continuall courſe held in the ſame all their flying time, vnleſſe on due conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and iuſt cauſe being moued to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie; as vnto a ſicke or craſie <hi>Hawke,</hi> with due reſpect vnto the eyes,<note place="margin">What ſhee gets by the labour of her body &amp; the vſe of her wings thriues beſt with her. Francke fedde with reſt breeds imperfection and glots the ſtomack.</note> or hot and eager mettelled <hi>Hawke;</hi> as alſo vnto the ſoundeſt and hardeſt <hi>Hawke</hi> that is, as when ſhee ſhall haue continual hard flying, and kills often, then may you with boldneſſe, and diſcretion in the quantitie, giue vnto her bloudy rewards, and three or foure times in the weeke ſuppers of the ſame, as of Partridge or Feſants heads and neckes, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good meate; alwayes being mindefull in time of reſt, that then you faile not to feed with meate cleane dreſſed, hard waſhed and dryed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:26902:23"/>
to hold the ſtomacke right and ſharpe withall;<note place="margin">The ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke.</note> for otherwiſe (that) being dulled and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, there is no content to be had, nor ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection to be looked for abroad, when ſhee is at libertie and her owne diſpoſing, but altogether offenſiueneſſe and vexation. For as I haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten told you (that) is the only marke you ought to ayme at, it ties and binds her to all other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions you can deſire to haue her furniſhed withall. And on the contrary, it ſeuers and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parates aſunder the one from the other, and makes her as a wilde and vntamed <hi>Hawke.</hi> Alſo it is very neceſſary that this one thing be well obſerued all the flying time, either to the field or couart, but eſpecially during that time,<note place="margin">The cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> becauſe then for the moſt part, the weather is diſpoſed to ſharpneſſe and cold: for which cauſe you ought not to ſuffer any <hi>Hawke</hi> of that kinde to be faſting too long;<note place="margin">The incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenience of long faſting.</note> for it breedeth much winde in them, the which they are all ſubiect vnto, and wil appeare often with a riſing in the gorge, and a noiſe withall of croking; the one may bee felt with the hand, and the other heard with the eare; and therefore both are as eaſie to bee iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of: likewiſe the rye and the cray very much attendeth on the ſame, and it is a ſpecial meanes, with cold adioyned, to take off her fleſh, which at that time of the yeare will not very eaſily bee put on againe, vnleſſe ſhee bee a right ſound <hi>Hawke:</hi> and on this impoueriſhment attendeth many other infirmities. Therefore to preuent
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:26902:24"/>
theſe or any other that may grow thereon; you ought to prouide for euery Hawking-day a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable meale of cleane dreſſed meat, the which you muſt keepe in a faire cloath: then in the morning,<note place="margin">That your Hawke be not kept fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting too long for her flying.</note> ſuddenly after ſhee hath caſt, giue her one bit when her hood is on. Alſo if you chance to ſpend an houre more before you finde your flight, giue her another bit; and ſo after this manner in your owne diſcretion. Afterwards, during the time of your recreation and ſporting abroad, compare or equall ſo your meate with the length or ſhortneſſe of time, as that ſhe ſhall neuer be ouer emptie, yet neuertheleſſe ſhal euer haue a perfect appetite, and good courage to fly after the beſt manner, and a well able and ſtrong bodie to maintaine the ſame withall, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe through long faſting would ſoone bee weakened and brought to poore eſtate. Alſo, as touching cold meate,<note place="margin">Of cold meate.</note> whenſoeuer you doe feed with any of it, it ſhall profit you nothing to waſh it, ſo be it be cleane; for the bloud therein being cold, the ſtrength therof for the moſt part is decayed, by which meanes it hath loſt the principall force and vigor of it, through the which it would the better haue fed and nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: I will aduiſe no man to vſe it, but as ſeldome as he may, for a continuance of it breeds pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and many other diſeaſes. On the contrary, to feed with hot meate,<note place="margin">The benefit of good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eate.</note> although at that time to be reaſonably well waſhed and dried, it holdeth health and ſtrength together, withall preuenting
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:26902:24"/>
the moſt, and continuall ſtriuing againſt all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of diſeaſes. And forget not whenſoeuer you ſet your <hi>Hawke</hi> downe off your fiſt hoodded or vnhoodded, to reſt, to weather, to bathe,<note place="margin">Of ſetting your Hawke downe to reſt.</note> or for what cauſe elſe ſoeuer, that you come not to take her vp againe to your fiſt, without vſing your voice in whiſtling or chirping vnto her, alſo with ſome bit of meat or a ſtumpe to pleaſe her withall; for ſo ſhall you worke in her an euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting loue and deſire of your comming and company: whereas otherwiſe to come vnto her ſtilly or ſilently, ſuddenly or raſhly to take her vp to your fiſt from her naturall deſire of quiet reſt,<note place="margin">Of taking her vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</note> and to bee alone without ſuch kinde vſage and louing content, it ſtirs vp in her, her owne naturall diſpoſition, which is vnto anger and feare, and to hate the ſocietie and company of the man, deſiring alwayes to bee at libetie, and out of his poſſeſſion.</p>
               <p>Alſo remember at all times you ſet your <hi>Hawke</hi> on her pearch hoodded, that ſhee may not haue vnderſtanding or perfect knowledge where it ſtandeth; for if ſhee haue, ſhee will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes haue an vnquiet longing to be there, and will not reſt quietly on the fiſt after ſhee is once within the dores; and eſpecially vntill ſhee bee throughly reclaimed and made flying, and hath beene wel flone, your fiſt for the moſt part muſt be her pearch, and ſhe ought to know no other; for they bee <hi>Hawkes</hi> that in their firſt making, with a little reſt will quickly forget what for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:26902:25"/>
they were taught, and returne to their wildeneſſe againe.</p>
               <p>Alſo, whenſoeuer you ſhall preceiue her to be vntoward or frowardly diſpoſed,<note place="margin">An obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation by the Hawke.</note> you ought not to reſiſt her with the like behauiour, as many a cholericke and haſty man will do; for ſhee will quickly perceiue and obſerue it, and her loue wil abate and be turned into diſdaine,<note place="margin">The pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Oſtringer towards his Hawke.</note> which at the preſent time you ſhall perceiue to appeare by her ſtrange and ſcornefull countenance in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding you; but you muſt alwayes be prepared and armed with patience and gentleneſſe to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure her vnquietneſſe, and euermore haue ſome ſtumpe in a readineſſe to appeaſe her anger, and quiet her withal, when you ſhal ſee her addicted thereunto, vntill you haue reclaimed and made her gentle indeed. And whereas I formerly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed, not to carry your <hi>Hawke</hi> faſting too long for her flying, but to diſtribute her portion vnto her by bits, as time and occaſion ſhould ſerue: ſo likewiſe I doe wiſh that in the time of in ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and reclaiming,<note place="margin">An order to be vſed at the firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming.</note> you doe not at any time giue her, her dinner altogether at one time, for thereby you ſhall prolong and deferre ſo much the more the time of her making; for ſo ſoone as her ſtomacke is ſatisfied and filled, her appetite and deſire towards you is choaked, and vntil the houre of feeding growes neere againe, her mind and remembrance is cleane off on you; whereas otherwiſe, as I haue ſaid, to diuide it in the fore-part of the day, and let her iumpe often to the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:26902:25"/>
fiſt for it, ſhe will ſtill be mindefull on you, and neuer forgetfull, but alwayes, and inwardly in her minde attending and liſtening for your voice, and ſome other pleaſing reward from you, and ſhee will ſo much the ſooner be made a perfect <hi>Hawke.</hi> There is no man that can at the firſt ſight of his <hi>Hawke</hi> truly iudge of her nature and diſpoſition, but therein ſhall be much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, they are ſo different in their kind; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it behoueth euery one to be carefull, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, at that time when ſhee is firſt to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred,<note place="margin">An obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation at the firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance.</note> that then he ſets or puts her vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the higheſt point or pin of hunger, doubting, as it were, the worſt of her, or making queſtion of her good or bad inclination; for thereby he ſhall ſuddenly perceiue and plainly ſee, all the ſpirit and mettle that naturally is in her; for when ſhee hath once taken her prey, whatſoeuer it be, although ſhee ſhould bee of a dull diſpoſition; yet by that meanes ſhee will rather chooſe to die then for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake it, ſhee will be ſo pinched with appetite and deſire to enioy it; wheras otherwiſe the ſtomack being vnperfect, the leaſt occaſion that may be,<note place="margin">The fruits of an imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke.</note> as the approch of her owne Keeper, or any other man, the appearing either of horſe or dogge, or what ſtrange ſight elſe ſoeuer, will be ſufficient to cauſe her to forſake it, and go her way; which ill condition ſhee will remember afterward, and be alwayes apt on the leaſt occaſion to doe the like againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:26902:26"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Of the <hi>Hauke</hi> that will not endure or abide the ſight of the hood.<figure/>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Very man, though he would neuer ſo faine, cannot bee ſo exquiſite, as to performe the ſlight and nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe of that arte, by quicke and cleanely conueying the hood on, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the hand, in regard that thoſe kinde of <hi>Hawks</hi> be naturally more coy and curious to be handled about the head then any other be; for which cauſe there be many men, that when they doe aſſay to put on their hood, doe eyther quite miſſe them, or otherwiſe put it halfe way or looſely on,<note place="margin">An error in the Keeper.</note> which greatly offendeth the <hi>Hawke;</hi> neuertheleſſe to adde more anger and vexation
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:26902:26"/>
to her, they will vſe the arte of bobbing with their hand or finger, vntil they haue euen almoſt cauſed her to fall backward for feare, before ſhe can be hoodded: this is a moſt vile qualitie, and vnſeemely to be vſed to any <hi>Hawke,</hi> and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to one of this kinde; for it will in the end beate her quite out of loue with the very ſight of the hood, or with the mouing but of the hand towards her head, although ſhee were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo gentle before.</p>
               <p>And therefore I doe wiſh euery one that would haue his <hi>Hawke</hi> gently diſpoſed that way, to forſake that one vnſeemely qualitie or vndecent order, and accept of another rule at my hand, which heere I ſhall expreſſe plainely and truely vnto you; and with the which I haue my ſelfe made diuers <hi>Hawkes,</hi> that hath beene frighted and feared in the higheſt degree, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come moſt louing and gentle againe.</p>
               <p>I doubt not but there be many will think this to be a very hard matter to performe, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it neuertheleſſe is a thing vnuſuall, and hath ſeldome or neuer beene ſeene. For triall wherof, let him that hath ſuch a <hi>Hawke,</hi> if he cannot doe it himſelfe, ſend her vnto me, and if I doe not make her as gentle as hee can deſire ſhee ſhould be, then for twentie ſhillings I will forfeit vnto him twentie nobles; and I will heere ſhew you the manner and way how to perfect the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:26902:27"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> To make the <hi>Goſhawke</hi> gentle, and to loue the hood, that hath with ill vſage beene bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten out of loue with all before.</head>
               <figure>
                  <head>GO SHAWKE.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Vring the time by day or night, that you doe carry one of theſe kind of <hi>Hawkes</hi> on your fiſt, that hath bin bobbed with the hood, as we may terme it: doe you alſo carry a hood of ſome note,<note place="margin">Obſerue wel this order.</note> I meane for the colour, on your finger, that may wel be ſeene and viewed by her, as it hangeth there<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but beware that you doe not ſhow it as yet with your other hand vnto her, but there let it reſt daily for a weeke together in her ſight, that ſhe may alſo feed cloſe by it: then
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:26902:27"/>
this being ſo done, alwayes after when you feed take it gently in your other hand, and moue and ſtirre it about her meate, that ſhee may touch it as ſhee eates; doe thus another weeke: euer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring, that after ſhe hath fed, it may reſt on your little finger againe in her ſight, till the next time, and yet not to be feared with it. You ſhall vſe this courſe, vntill you ſee that without any feare ſhee will but thus endure it; which being perceiued, you muſt then hold your meat in the hand that ſhee ſitteth on, and with the other hand hold the hood by the taſſel vpon her meat, mouing and ſtirring it, as though you would keepe her from feeding; but it muſt bee done ſoftly and gently, when as you ſhall perceiue that ſhee will then ſtriue to feed beſides it: then with leſſe ſhew or appearance of meate in the hand, you ſhall hold the hood by the taſſell iuſt ouer the meate, that you may ſee in your owne diſcretion, that ſhee muſt needes eate cleane tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row it: doe thus ſo long, as vntill you ſee that ſhee will feed and ſearch boldly cleane thorow the hood for her meate, and eate it without any ſnatching or feare, alwayes being mindfull of the ſtomacke, then may you bee bold, as ſhee feeds, a little with your hand to moue the hood off and on the meate, and ſhee will take no of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence at all.</p>
               <p>Alſo, as ſhee is feeding, and doth thruſt tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the hood for her meate, doe you beare the hood a little againſt her, and ſhee will hood and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:26902:28"/>
vnhood her ſelfe as often as you will haue her: then whereas before you ought to haue reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned her, from taking too much hold of her meate; on the contrary, now when ſhee hath with your aſſiſtance put on her owne hood, let her cat freely vntill ſhe hath done, and take it off no more vntill feeding time againe; and in this manner, within the moneth and leſſe, ſhee will be wonne to hood her ſelfe with the leaſt ſtump you doe carry about you, as often as you ſhall haue occaſion.</p>
               <p>And for thoſe <hi>Hawkes,</hi> there is none that keepes them, but ought alwayes to haue ſome ſuch thing about him: And then doe but iudge whether he were better to vſe this ready courſe that will neuer faile him, then to bobbe at her aboue the hand vntill hee hath quite ſpoiled her.</p>
               <p>And forget not, that if ſhee be a <hi>Hawke</hi> taken from the Mew, or otherwiſe, that you neuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne to practiſe this courſe with her, vntill her ſtomacke be perfectly come to her; for if you doe, it will marre her for euer, and ſhee will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be reclaimed againe; for it is that eſpecially that draweth, and alſo forceth her to become louing and friendly to that which ſhee formerly hated.</p>
               <p>Thus haue I heretofore in ſome ſort ſhewed you, how ſtrange and coy a <hi>Hawke</hi> the <hi>Goſhawke</hi> is; nice and curious to be handled; how apte ſhee is to take diſlike at any trifling toy: and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:26902:28"/>
therefore as I haue formerly aduiſed for other <hi>Hawkes,</hi> ſo eſpecially for her, you had neede to to be more circumſpect and carefull with all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent heed at her firſt reclaiming and making; for as ſhee is then faſhioned, ſhee will euer after with reaſonable paines and gouernment frame her ſelfe towards you in all her actions. And I will heere, according to mine owne ſimple skill and order vſed in mine owne practiſe, ſhew you the way vnto the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> To reclaime the <hi>Hawke</hi> from the Cage.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen you ſhall haue one of theſe <hi>Hawks</hi> brought firſt vnto your hand, it is meete that by your arte and beſt endeauour, you doe then prepare and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:26902:29"/>
make her readie to bee reclaimed after this manner.</p>
               <p>Giue her a fortnights carriage or more as ſhe is in her rufter-hood,<note place="margin">Obſerue this order.</note> alwayes ſtroaking and playing with her, with your hand, or a feather in ſtead thereof; and alſo in her diet, to be as care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to feed cleane with waſhed meate, by which meanes ſhee may be brought the ſooner to haue a good ſtomacke, and be gentle and well pleaſed to be handled, which you ſhall finde afterwards to be a great benefit and furthering in her reclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and making: then when you haue ſo done and taken that paines with her, and that you do finde her to bee gentle indeed, and pliable to your will; (the which you ſhall perceiue by her griping and liſtning to your voice, whiſtle or chirping, or eager feeding:)</p>
               <p>Then hauing one euening your water with pepper prouided, and when you haue, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the order and accuſtomed manner, well waſhed and peppered her, take off her rufter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, being ſure to haue another that is fit and eaſie to be put on; and likewiſe afterward now and then, as you ſhall ſee iuſt cauſe, when as you ſhall find her ſo meeke and gently diſpoſed, that you may doe what you liſt with her: whereas otherwiſe without this former paines and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, ſhee would altogether haue wanted a ſtomacke, and continued ſo much the longer, both rammage and wilde, the which would haue deſerued much more paines and labour of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:26902:29"/>
her Keeper. But to returne, as ſhee groweth a little to be drie, put on her hood, and giue her a bit of good meate vpon it, to pleaſe and refreſh her withall; and ſo holding this courſe to hood gently and vnhood, now and then not forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting her reward euer after it is on, vntill ſhee bee throughly dryed, and afterwards the moſt part of the night; then you may ſet her downe bare faced, to haue two or three houres ſleepe or reſt; and be ſure it be in a ſpeciall warme place,<note place="margin">A good ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueat.</note> and on a drie and warme pearch on high, for thoſe kinde of <hi>Hawkes</hi> bee very ſubiect to take cold, and apte to haue the crampe on ſuch occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
               <p>Thus when ſhee and your ſelfe hath taken a little reſt, then ſee that you doe draw by degrees ſoftly vnto her, with ſhew of meat in your hand, withall vſing your voice or tongue, with chir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and whiſtling vnto her, vntill you haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken her gently to your fiſt; when as diuiding one meale into ſeuerall parts, beſtow it ſo on her for the moſt part after her hood is put on: and to continue this order with her in the day time for a while, it will be very good, vntill you doe finde her well reclaimed; for it will cauſe her to looke for the hood, and take delight to haue it put on, when ſhee ſhall finde her ſelfe alwayes ſo well rewarded and pleaſed afterward.</p>
               <p>And as I haue heretofore giuen you to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that euery <hi>Hawke</hi> is not alike in their naturall diſpoſition, but are much differing the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:26902:30"/>
one from the other: ſo alſo and therefore you ought to bee the more carefull to obſerue and marke diligently how ſhee is diſpoſed, and to order and rule her according to the ſame. For example,<note place="margin">Obſerue the nature of the Hauke.</note> if you doe finde her to bee tutchie or nicely addicted, and curious to entertaine and accept of your hand and the hood to come neare her head; then muſt you forbeare to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe and bee doing often in the day time with her: but as I haue ſhewed you, ſeldome, but at her feeding, or elſe late in the night time, when as you ſhall finde her more willing to take the ſame.</p>
               <p>Thus hauing ſo wel &amp; perfectly accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed your deſire in her reclaiming familiarity and imboldening: it wil now be good time to teach her to iumpe and come to the fiſt, euer being mindfull of the ſtomack that it may be perfect; for as I haue let you to vnderſtand, how coy and ſtately a bird the <hi>Goſhawke</hi> is, and whereas other <hi>Hawkes</hi> of contrary kinde are vſed to come to a Lure, throwne ſome diſtance from the man: contrariwiſe, ſhee being a <hi>Hawke</hi> of the fiſt, muſt, if ſhe be vſed and taught as ſhee ought to be, be made to come home cloſe to the body of the man, with boldneſſe to his hand, and ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with great familiaritie, and without any feare to ſeize and ſit vpon the ſame, during his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; which ſhee will neuer bee forced to doe with all the arte in the world, if her ſtomacke be any whit imperfect.</p>
               <figure/>
               <p>And whereas many a man glorieth and dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth himſelfe worthie of great praiſe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, for his extraordinarie haſte and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition: I doe maintaine the contrary, ſaying, there is no ſuch cauſe of deſeruing, for he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth on blindly and raſhly,<note place="margin">Vaine glory.</note> without iudgement or conſideration of what marke hee aymeth at; and when hee thinketh hee hath made a ſound and a good concluſion, afterwards it ſhall bee found imperfect,<note place="margin">The low and poore Hawke is euermore ſubiect to infirmitie.</note> and hee ſhall be new to ſeeke, for his <hi>Hawke</hi> hath hardly bin taught one good qualitie or artificiall condition.</p>
               <p>Alſo he cannot chooſe but pull off her fleſh, whereby her haughtineſſe is abated, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priueth
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:26902:31"/>
her of her mettle and courage, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely ſpoileth the <hi>Hawke:</hi> for there is not any one of that kinde that will flye well, how good ſoeuer ſhee either was or is, being any whit im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poueriſhed or brought low; neither will they laſt healthfull, but will bee alwayes ſubiect to ſickneſſe, through one infirmitie or other that ariſeth thereon.</p>
               <p>Therefore whoſoeuer coueteth to keepe a <hi>Hawke</hi> of that nature and kind, expecting plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and contentment from her, with health and ſtrength together to maintaine the ſame, muſt not faile to take good time to teach her, and then by his arte and diligent endeauour he ſhall not be any way deceiued, but moſt aſſuredly ſhall finde all the ſpirit and mettle that natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally was carried or bred in her.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:26902:32"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> How and in what manner the <hi>Goſhawke</hi> ought to be called looſe, and taught to draw, and in what places, for the better auoiding of ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences as ſhee is ſubiect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and may befall in that time.</head>
               <figure>
                  <head>GO SHAWKE.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow will it be good time to let her be called looſe, when as it is expedient that you doe ſhun all places neare vnto your own home, other houſes or townes, to auoid ſuch inconueniences, as through temptations may grow thereon, as Powltering or Doue-houſes, and ſuch like pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the which all thoſe <hi>Hawkes</hi> be ſubiect vnto;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:26902:32"/>
and hauing once caught ſuch an ill propertie,<note place="margin">The ſpoile of the Hawke.</note> they will very ſedome or neuer bee reclaimed from it, but will follow it, how farre ſoeuer from any towne ſhee ſhall be flone; yet if ſhee be not ſuddenly ſerued and pleaſed, ſhee will not ſtay, but forthwith will fall to raling; neuer once loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king backe to her Keeper, vntill ſhee cometh there whereas ſhee will ſerue her ſelfe too ſoone.<note place="margin">To a towne.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And thus to conſider what a toyle and vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion this muſt needs bring to him that ſhall fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low her; it would make any man care and couet with all diligence to preuent ſuch a miſchiefe at the firſt, before it doe come: the which to effect, this courſe you muſt take; walke with her to the young woods or groues betimes in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone, hauing before prepared her ſtomacke fit and readie for the ſame purpoſe,<note place="margin">Obſerue this order at her firſt teaching to draw.</note> and there put her vp into a tree, walking along from her into the winde, vſing your voice vnto her ſoftly, as though you had <hi>Spaniels</hi> with you, and ſpake to them, but let it be eſpecially with your tongue in whiſtling and chirping vnto her; by which meanes to cauſe her draw and follow after you with little noiſe, which if ſhee ſhall ſo doe, as there is no doubt, but that ſhee will frame her ſelfe according to your expectation; then ſuffer her not too long, but call her to your fiſt againe, and reward her a little with ſome bit of meate to pleaſe her withall; the which it is fitte you ſhould haue in a readineſſe wrapped in a faire
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:26902:33"/>
cloath, vnleſſe you haue either Pigeon, Rooke, or ſome other ſuch like thing about you, out of the which you may draw a legge, and ſo content her.</p>
               <p>After this, you ſhall put her vp againe, and ſo by your ſofteſt voice or whiſtle draw her along after you againe; for it is not good, neither con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient to vſe a lowde voice or noiſe vnto her for diuers reſpects.<note place="margin">Why you ought not to call her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowde.</note> For firſt, it will be a meanes to teach her ſit and loyter behind you, ſo farre as ſhee can heare you, which is one ill qualitie; otherwiſe ſomtime a man wil go with his <hi>Hawke</hi> where hee would be loath either to be heard or ſeen, as I muſt confeſſe, I haue done my ſelf ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a time; which he cannot do with ſuch a one as firſt hath beene taught, and is ſtill wonted to loude voices; but he muſt make, as it were, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation where-abouts he goes, and where hee is: whereas otherwiſe hee may goe ſafely and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely, and his <hi>Hawke</hi> will draw and follow him, as diligently and attentiuely, by meanes ſhee was at the firſt tutored and taught with a ſtill voice or whiſtle.</p>
               <p>Alſo your <hi>Spaniels</hi> will hunt within your command, and ſo neere you and your <hi>Hawke,</hi> as they ſhall neuer ſpring any thing out of her danger, but ſtill where ſhee may commaund it: whereas otherwiſe in hearing of lowde noiſes they will range far off, and at randon, ſpringing out of the way far from you; which wil be much diſpleaſing both vnto the man and the <hi>Hawke.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:26902:33"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> To make loue and vnity betweene the <hi>Oſtringer</hi> himſelfe, his <hi>Hawke,</hi> and his <hi>Spaniels;</hi> which is a ſpeciall thing to bee obſerued.</head>
               <figure>
                  <head>GO SHAWKE.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow that you haue after this foreſaid rule and order pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed vnto you, taught your <hi>Hawke</hi> to draw dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently after you, &amp; to come againe as readily to your fiſt: It is as meete and neceſſarie that you doe prouide you of ſuch <hi>Spaniels</hi> as you intend to <hi>Hawke</hi> withall: and becauſe this <hi>Hawke</hi> is a bird very obſeruing, and will quickly learne to know her Keeper, and be familiar with
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:26902:34"/>
him, and ſeeme as ſtrange and coy to let another man come neare her: alſo to haue ſuch vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of <hi>Spaniels,</hi> as to know and loue one that ſhall be continually in company with her, and as it were to hate or be fearefull of another that comes but ſeldome to her: alſo many of the kind will be very fearefull, nice and coy of al dogges, and at the firſt ſight will not abide or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure any.</p>
               <p>Wherefore now that you haue formerly in all other points of perfection, by your arte, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and diſcretion, accompliſhed your deſire with her: it is now that you ought through all diligence, to practiſe and labour to breed a fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar league of friendſhip, loue and vnitie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene your ſelfe,<note place="margin">To breede loue between the Hawke and the Spaniels.</note> your <hi>Hawke,</hi> and your <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niels;</hi> the which to accompliſh and bring to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, take this courſe. At euery feeding time draw you all conueniently together, whereas you muſt let your <hi>Hawke</hi> feede amongſt the dogges on your fiſt very oft; not one dogge or two, as I haue ſaid before, for ſhe will learne too ſoone to know him too well; but amongſt two or three couple, or as many as you haue, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to haue the dead pelt of a Pullet or Hen in a ſhort cruce, and throwing it oftentimes from you in the thickeſt amongſt them, that ſhee may flie from your fiſt, and eagerly choppe amongſt them and ſeaze vpon the ſame; there ſuffering her to plume awhile, then take her vp againe with a ſtumpe to your fiſt, immediatly throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:26902:34"/>
it, as before, againe and againe euen in the middeſt of them: and this courſe you muſt vſe euery day, vntill you doe find that ſhee will ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter very boldly, and without any feare,<note place="margin">By this you ſhall know when your Hawke is ready to fly.</note> amongſt them all; and then you ſhall perceiue that ſhee will haue pereeiuerance and vnderſtanding by the dogs remouing and giuing way with feare vnto her, that ſhee hath euen gotten the vpper hand and maſtery of them; whereas otherwiſe to haue flone, or offered to enter her before, without theſe former preparations and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie courſes, it had beene done raſhly without iudgement; and there is not one <hi>Hawke</hi> amongſt twentie, but would haue beene beaten out of loue both with the man, the <hi>Spaniels,</hi> and whatſoeuer beſides hee had flone her vnto. And ſo I will omitte to ſpeake any more of this point in this place, becauſe I purpoſe to inlarge it fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as I ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:26902:35"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIIII.</hi> How you ſhall firſt enter your <hi>Hawke,</hi> and teach her flye to the field, and to order and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage her there during that ſeaſon.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen you haue, as I formerly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſed, well reclaimed, imbol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened and taught your <hi>Hawke</hi> to know and vnderſtand her owne ſuperioritie and command ouer her ſeruants:<note place="margin">The Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niels.</note> it wil be good to prepare and make her ready to fly, &amp; it is meet to enter her firſt to the field, when as ſhee ought eſpecially to bee skilfully ordered, flone, followed, and aſſiſted; for commonly a direct and perfect beginning, doth giue proofe and cauſe of good effects and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:26902:35"/>
concluſion. Therefore your ſureſt courſe is, to prouide, if it bee poſſible, three or foure hand Partridge, with a companion, friend, or ſeruant, and one couple of ſtanch <hi>Spaniels;</hi> then goe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the faireſt field, hauing before prepared and armed your <hi>Hawke,</hi> with appetite and courage to flye after the beſt manner, for her owne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and giue content to the beholder; sand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there in a readineſſe, one of you ſhall goe neare hand from the other,<note place="margin">The buſhes.</note> to ſome buſhes or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſmall couart of obſcuritie to be ſhadowed, whereas hee ſhall ſpend his voice to the dogges, after the accuſtomed maner, vſing ſome blowes with his pole, and beating his harmeleſſe enemy withall, as from forth the ſame; he ſhall ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly let the Partridge ſpring, with ſuch iudgement in the deliuery, that the <hi>Hawke</hi> may diſcerne and ſee it, and crying with a lowd voyce, Howe,<note place="margin">Words of cuſtome.</note> howe, howe, that ſhee may haue vnderſtanding, and learne to know the word of aduertiſement or warning, when ſhee ſhould at any other time looke about her, or be watchfull to take the beſt opportunitie offered at an inſtant vnto her, for her beſt aduantage.</p>
               <p>This being well effected, and that the <hi>Hawke</hi> doth with ſpirit and mettle flye after and take it,<note place="margin">The Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridge.</note> be yee ſure with all expedition and ſwiftneſſe, that your <hi>Horſe,</hi> or owne ſupporters may afford to get into her, and thereby ſtand and guide or guard her, that no dogge nor other cauſe may fright or feare her, whereby to depriue her of the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:26902:36"/>
prey ſhee hath ſo hotly purſued, ſo lately taken, and deſireth ſo much to enioy and keepe within her owne poſſeſſion; but with your licence and good leaue doe ſuffer her to plume and take her pleaſure on the ſame: And with your further ayde and aſſiſtance, to take blood thereon, ſtill hauing the <hi>Spaniels</hi> in ſight cloſe by her. All this well practiſed, then you muſt teach her to take the head in her foote, and eate it on the ground; and when ſhee hath ſo done, and looketh about her: hauing your <hi>Spaniels</hi> by you, throw the Partridge pelt, as before you had vſed to doe in her firſt teaching, once amongſt the dogges, and let her take it, being in her leaſh, that ſhee may not carrie it from you; and whileſt ſhe ſits there and plumes, make her ſupper readie; take her gently to your fiſt, and there content her: then walking towards your home, with ioy in your ſucceſſe, and much good likelihood to haue no worſe thereafter, you may well conſider and determine of the next oportunitie, and after the ſame maner how to order and vſe her; by which meanes, no doubt but you ſhall very ſuddenly attaine to your owne expected deſire, and haue an excellent <hi>Hawke,</hi> and by all meanes flye her to the field all the firſt yeare, and let her not ſee the Feſant at all, for that will draw her loue from the Partridge, and make her giue them ouer; nay, he that will haue a good <hi>Hawke</hi> to the field of this kinde,<note place="margin">Obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> muſt neuer let her ſee the Feſant at all, nor flye one flight thereunto; for the beſt of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:26902:36"/>
them will take more delight in the one, then in the other, and grow quite out of loue with the one for the others ſake.</p>
               <p>Now when you haue thus well and luckily entred and bloudded her with theſe Partridges, and alſo killed ſome three or foure more from the marke, at the reteriue, and that you doe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue by her, that ſhee once knowes a Partridge by ſight; the whoorr, and other accuſtomed termes vſed, and will goe readily from the fiſt thereunto:</p>
               <p>Be ye ſure after, that al the forepart of the yeer you let her goe no more one flight in ten, neare vnto the riſing of her game; for that will cauſe her to girde and maſter them, as it were, at the ſowce, within a ſhort ſpace, being no way able in that ſeaſon to make wing, to hold out before ſuch a <hi>Hawke;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Obſerue wel this order.</note> and alſo ſhee will afterward re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member and looke for the ſame order, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it will not flie towards the latter end of the yeere; no, ſhee will make you beleeue ſhee ſees them not at all, neither will flye after ſuch a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridge as ſhall be ſprung farre from her, but to the next tree ſhee meetes withall, and being ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo good a mettled <hi>Hawke,</hi> this courſe will ſpoile her; for ſhee will as well vnderſtand the difference betweene the one and the other, as your ſelfe; and what ſhee cannot doe at hand, ſhee will neuer doe.</p>
               <p>And therefore conſidering that this order and courſe held long at the beginning of the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:26902:37"/>
yeare, while Partridge be but weake, is ſufficient to make ſlothfull, and to marre the beſt mettel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Hawke</hi> that is, you ought to be more careful when you meete with another that is but of a dull diſpoſition, and as ſluggiſh of her wings: yet I haue ſeene ſuch a one, through the arte and well ordering of her Keeper, hath proued a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall <hi>Hawke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">An exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</note>It was once mine owne chance to haue ſuch a one in my cuſtodie, that in her falling I percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to be very ſluggiſh and heauie, which ſoone altered my opinion of her, and withdrew my former affection almoſt quite from her: yet on further conſideration I began to think with my ſelfe, that ſeeing I had gone ſo farre with her, I would not ſo leaue her, for a little more paines, vntill I had had ſome further triall of her; and then this direct courſe I tooke preſently with her.</p>
               <p>It was very early of the yeare whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as I ſhewed her markt Partridge, that I ſprung, and ſuffered to reſt long after: of the which, and after this manner, ſhee killed me, in two or three dayes, ſome two or three brace, euen at the catch, in a very little ſpace; in ſo much as I perceiued by her ready going, that ſhee knew them well, and alſo was very hot on them, and as buſily diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with them, when ſhee had any one in her foote: which alſo ſhewed, as I deemed, ſome good loue in her towards them, and gaue mee ſome further comfort beſides, and hope of a
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:26902:37"/>
good concluſion. Afterward in proceſſe of time it was my happe to ſhew her diuers Partridge, that were ſprung further from mee, then ſhee was vſed to fly, to the which I offred my <hi>Hawke;</hi> but after the old prouerbe, <hi>Who ſo blinde, as hee that will not ſee?</hi> and ſo my <hi>Hawke</hi> would none, but caſt her regards another way.</p>
               <p>After which, I began to call to minde and conſider of her ill nature, and alſo of my owne fooliſh and former error, how that I had too long at firſt taught her to ſnatch and catch them vp at ſowce, and nuzled her too much therein: Likewiſe, that I obſerued no times, but flew her at aduenture and out of ſeaſon, as too early, or in the heate of the day: neither had I any due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect vnto her ſtomacke.</p>
               <p>And thus all things being thought on, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to reſt her two or three dayes: and whereas at the firſt, when ſhee pleaſed mee, I was too louing and fond on her, and alſo did too richly reward her (which hath beene a fault in my ſelfe, I am ſure, and, I thinke, in many an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.)</p>
               <p>But to returne, during the time of reſt that I gaue her, I fed her very cleane, and ſoaked her meate all the day or night in vrine, the which is a ſpeciall. thing for a hard and dull mettelled <hi>Hawke</hi> of this kind, to whether a good ſtomack withall.</p>
               <p>And when I had ſo done, I ſhewed her ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther couie of Partridge late in the euening, or
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:26902:38"/>
towards the euening, for too late is as bad as to early for a <hi>Hawke</hi> to flye; but theſe ſprung a great way from mee, and went all whole toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: ſhee being at that time well armed with an eager appetite, and a good edge ſet on her, ſpurs ſufficient to put her on, and pricke her forward after the beſt manner; ſhee well perceiuing of them, thruſt her ſelfe vp from my fiſt a great height, and went after them, but altogether on playnes, euen Buſſard like, yet neuertheleſſe ſhe did rightly marke them; and at my comming in to the reteriue, the <hi>Spaniels</hi> ſprung one to her, the which ſhee flew very hard and killed: and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this, hauing good reſpect vnto her ſtomacke, and alſo for a while obſeruing well the time to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the euening, ſhee prooued an excellent <hi>Hawke,</hi> yet neuer mended the maner of her firſt flights, but alwaies flue them very jadiſhly, and made no haſte at all: yet afterward, when Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridge were ſprung, although ſhee went a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long behinde, ſhee would not faile to haue one often in her foote, the which I imagined ſhee did euer take comming cunningly; and eſpecially after the leafe were off, you might haue ventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ten to one, in the woodlands ſhe would not faile to haue one in her foote.</p>
               <p>By this appeareth, that this <hi>Hawke</hi> did know her owne vnableneſſe, and that ſhee were not fit nor able through the wightneſſe of her wings, to make yeeld or maſter the faſt flying Partridg, and that if ſhee had beene wilde, to haue ſhifted
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:26902:38"/>
for her ſelfe, ſhee muſt haue vſed her policie to haue caught her prey, or elſe oftentimes to haue faſted.</p>
               <p>Alſo this ſheweth as plainely, how eaſily this or any other dul mettelled <hi>Hawke</hi> might or may be marred, for want of iudgement and skill in her Keeper, or otherwiſe by his arte and paines taking, bee make and taught to doe him right good ſeruice; although not altogether out of her owne ſpirit and mettle, yet through his arte and her policie.</p>
               <p>Alſo you muſt haue this reſpect, and bee mindfull of one ill propertie that many of thoſe <hi>Hawkes</hi> bee ſubiect vnto, which is, that when they haue flone a Partridge hard to any couart,<note place="margin">An ill qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie to fall on the ground.</note> and takes it not at the firſt flight, there will they ſit ſtill on the ground, and will not get vp to any ſtand for their better vantage; which is a moſt vilde, fooliſh, and dull condition.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, as I haue before aduiſed at the firſt entrance, it is meete that you take but a few <hi>Spaniels</hi> abroad with you, and alſo to be ſuch as you may command vnto you after you haue flone, vntill you haue ſought and found your <hi>Hawke</hi> againe: for otherwiſe you ſhall neuer en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her; they wil euermore retriue the Partridge, that ſhee ſhall neuer ſee it as ſhee ſits on the ground.</p>
               <p>Therefore, to preuent the one in the dogges,<note place="margin">To amend this fault.</note> and to amend the other in the <hi>Hawke,</hi> take this courſe: when your <hi>Hawke</hi> hath flone a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridge,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:26902:39"/>
make after with all ſpeed that you can, taking your dogges with you, by your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and when you haue found her, be ſure to take her vp, but not on your fiſt by any meanes, if there be either hedge or tree neere hand, but take her by the bodie or ſhoulders ſuddenly with both your hands, and throw her vpon ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hedge, buſh, or tree, and then beate for the Partridge, when as it is vnpoſſible but ſhee muſt needs ſee it, if it doe ſpring then; if ſhee flye af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and kill it after that manner, you can deſire no more; for one ſo killed, is worth ten at the firſt flight, or otherwiſe from the ground. This courſe being wel followed, wil certainly reclaime her from that fault, &amp; teach her to riſe her ſelfe; for ſhee will quickly learne to vnderſtand, that elſe ſhee ſhall be caught and toſte vp; and ſo ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſome little feare of that one thing, and alſo knowledge that afterward ſhee ſhall enioy ſome pleaſure and content thereby, ſhee will ſo much the ſooner grow perfect, and jumpe vp her ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Some man when he comes in to his <hi>Hawke,</hi> and findes her after that manner, on the ground, will preſently draw forth ſome meate or other,<note place="margin">A great er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror.</note> to take her to his fiſt withall, and there will hold her, expecting the riſing of her game: but ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is great indiſcretion in him ſo to doe; for there he teaches her with incouragement to ſit ſtill attending his owne comming to her, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a preſent reward expected from himſelfe, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:26902:39"/>
minding the prey, ſhee had ſo hotly purſued before: but without his future care and beſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, doth cleane forget the ſame: thus is ſhee quite ouerthrowne, and ten to one will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer after learne nor care to know her beſt aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</p>
               <p>But ſome man may anſwere and ſay againe, Why? this courſe to take and throw her vp af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that faſhion, muſt needs feare her, and make her vnwilling to come to her Keeper another time, when he ſhall be moſt deſirous of her. But it is not ſo, for you are to vnderſtand that it is not the <hi>Haggart,</hi> or right <hi>Rammage Hawke,</hi> that I meane; for you ſhall not once in your life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time know any of thoſe <hi>Hawkes</hi> to haue that fooliſh condition.</p>
               <p>But if it ſhould ſo fall out in ſome one eager and hot mettelled <hi>Hawke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</note> that out of her excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding loue to the thing ſhee hath flone, doe at her firſt entrance a little ſit, and hunt or ſeeke for it; and therefore to ſerue her ſo, it will bee no whit diſpleaſing vnto her, but ſhee will ſo much the ſooner (being luckily ſerued and pleaſed after) rightly vnderſtand the fruites and meaning of the ſame, and alſo will loue her Keeper neuer the worſe, but learne to know her better aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage: and whenſoeuer you ſhall finde a right <hi>Ramage Hawke</hi> to haue this qualitie, as at the fall of a Partridge to be downe and vp, to flye and to runne amongſt the dogges and men with bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, you may be aſſured, that with care now
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:26902:40"/>
and then to vſe her after that maner, with other good gouernment duely extended towards her by her Keeper, ſhee will moſt certainly proue a ſpeciall <hi>Hawke,</hi> for in that kinde of behauiour ſhee truely ſhewes her good nature; her hot loue and eager deſire to her game, and that in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of (that) for the preſent time ſhee owneth neither man, horſe nor dogge, nor any other thing, her minde is ſo bent of her pleaſure.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A fault in the Eyas.</note>But to leaue her, and returne to the <hi>Eyas, Brancher,</hi> or <hi>Puler,</hi> vnleſſe they bee bred of the better crye; you ſhall haue many of them, nay, the moſt part of them will haue that one condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, laſting and continuing with them a long time; and without this one remedie or meanes lately expreſſed, euen many yeers: which then I referre vnto you to be cenſured, whether a man were better to terrifie and feare her cleane out of her wittes, then ſo long to waite and ſtay, expecting her future and vncertaine deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings.</p>
               <p>But to returne backe againe to the <hi>Ramage Hawke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Of the Ramage Hawke. An exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</note> I will giue you an inſtance by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of (one) the which I had of late time in my hand, and kept vnder my owne gouernment at the leaſt a dozen yeares, and free from any one ill propertie or condition, during that time; but as I made her at the firſt, ſo I kept her to the end, and ſhee was a ſpeciall <hi>Hawke</hi> for eyther Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridge or Feſant.</p>
               <p>And this courſe, which here I ſhal preſcribe,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:26902:40"/>
I tooke with her in her firſt making, keeping, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering and flying. In the beginning I perceiued her to be very tutchie and coy to bee handled, for which cauſe I tooke extraordinary paynes with her, and made her very louing and gentle to the hood, euen as any <hi>Falcon</hi> was: alſo to the dogges I found her, in my practiſe, inclined ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to mine owne deſire and expectation: And ſo to omitte other circumſtances, courſe or order, as touching her calling, comming, or drawing.</p>
               <figure/>
               <p>Alſo at the ſame time I had in charge at the leaſt two caſt of <hi>Riuar-Hawks,</hi> and ordered them in their diet my ſelfe; for which cauſe I did very ſeldome flye her, ſometime not in the weeke and more, during which time, ſhee ſate for the moſt part in a rufter hood; and if I had not a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie conuenient place both day and night in the ſame, neuertheleſſe that time of reſt being expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, hauing occaſion to vſe her, eyther to the field or couart, and giuing her but one houre or two to weather abroad in the ayre, though ſtill in the Hood, with conſideration alwayes of the ſtomacke, ſhee would flye to content you. And this <hi>Hawke</hi> was ſo hot and eager at her firſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, that ſhee would at the reterine alwayes be
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:26902:42"/>
downe among the dogges, as it were, ſcambling for the Partridge; and whenſoeuer I came in, I would take her by the ſhoulders, betweene my hands, and throw her vp; nay, ouer and aboue, when a Partridge hath ſprung on the other ſide the hedge, where ſhee could not ſee it, I haue af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſame maner throwne her cleane ouer the ſame, and ſhee hath killed it in the foote at the ſame flight. This <hi>Hawke</hi> very quickly prooued very cunning, and as long as ſhe liued, when ſhe knew that ſhee had maſtered a Partridge, and that the dogges and men came in and tooke it, or elſe ſcambled for it, ſhee would neuer faile to make one, and bee a chiefe ſtickler in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate; and what dogge ſoeuer tooke it, he ſhould be ſure to leaue it, with ſome taſte of her diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and correction for it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Such hauks hath the true mettle.</note>Thus hauing, according to my beſt vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, ſhewed how to enter the <hi>Goſhawke</hi> to field, and to order and gouerne her during that ſeaſon, I will now proceede to the Couart, and out of the like knowledge appoint by preſcription how ſhee ought to be entred, flone, followed, and manned, during that time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:26902:42"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> How to enter the <hi>Goſhawke</hi> to the Couart.</head>
               <figure>
                  <head>GO SHAWKE.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ny man whoſe skill and knowledge by time and experience is approo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to be good,<note place="margin">To teach the Goſhawke to flye to the Couart.</note> may be fit and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently able of himſelfe to take the wilde <hi>Hawke</hi> from the Cage, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe to reclaime her and make her readie in due time to be flone; and alſo to flye her him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, or let her goe from his fiſt vnto her flight: neuertheleſſe, when ſhe is once gone or departed from him therunto, he may be then as much vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient or vnable to gouerne her during that time; for there be many men that are expert in their arte, and through their owne knowledge well able to teach one of thoſe kinde of <hi>Hawkes</hi>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:26902:43"/>
to flye, yet afterwards is no way able to follow and man her in her flight: whereby and through which cauſe, as ſhee was at firſt artificially and well made, ſo ſhee will bee then altogether as ſoone, or more ſooner cleane ſpoiled and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Euery one is not fit to keepe the Goſhawke.</note>If this bee true, then it appeareth that euery one is not fit to keepe the <hi>Goſhawke,</hi> although his iudgement be great; nor otherwiſe any one that hath not a well able bodie to follow her, as ſhee ought to be.</p>
               <p>But ſome man may anſwere, and ſay againe, that his body ſhall be well mounted and carried forward on horſe-backe; to the which I allow alſo, ſo farre as vntill hee commeth to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uart, but no further, vnleſſe hee will alwayes make choyce of his deſired or wiſhed place, the which no man can euer doe, to finde his game with ſpeed: neither in moſt Countries or places is there any choyce to be had; but to that ſport and with that <hi>Hawke,</hi> he muſt altogether truſt to his feete, or elſe tarry behinde; which, as I think, there is few men but would be loath ſo to doe, that beareth any loue to their <hi>Hawke,</hi> or the game they haue flone her vnto.</p>
               <p>Therefore it is moſt certaine that there is no one man can order and manage the <hi>Goſhawke</hi> to the Couart, but hee that hath a ſtrong and able bodie, with ſpirit, mettle, and courage adioyned thereunto, to follow her withall; and vnto ſuch a one, I will heere according to mine owne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:26902:43"/>
and opinion ſhew the way, how and in what places is beſt and meeteſt firſt to enter her in, and how to follow and manage her, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he hath made her a perfect <hi>Hawke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You may well remember that you haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie paſſed one good ſteppe forward on your iourney, and as you would thinke, eſcaped all the danger in your further pretended way, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect that you haue ſo artificially reclaimed, fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and flone your <hi>Hawke</hi> all this long time to the field, and haue ordered and gouerned her with good ſucceſſe in all your proceedings: but you ought to conſider neuertheleſſe,<note place="margin">Marke wel.</note> that this hath beene wrought, practiſed and brought to good concluſion, for the moſt part in the open and champane fields, where was the aſſiſtance of men on horſe-backe, and on foot, that might and haue come in at their pleaſures, to guard the <hi>Hawke,</hi> and preuent any ill accident that might befall by the <hi>Spaniels</hi> in their haſte or raſhneſſe, or otherwiſe happen vnto her.</p>
               <p>Therefore you are to conſider, that now you otherwiſe intend to make her to the Feſant; and for that thoſe kinde of Fowles doe altogether frequent and haunt the woods,<note place="margin">The man cannot fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low by view to ſuccour his Hawke.</note> and other places of obſcuritie, the which muſt needs be a blemiſh and hinderance to the ſight which ſhould giue directions in the flight; for the better effecting of your deſire, you ought to make good choice and be charie of what place you doe firſt enter her in, and eſpecially that ſhee may be there wel
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:26902:44"/>
guarded and kept from taking any diſlike or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence at the dogges, the which if ſhee ſhould doe in the beginning, ſhee will neuer endure them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; for as I haue ſaid before, it muſt bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered that the former familiaritie betweene them was bred in the field, whereas the <hi>Hawke</hi> for the moſt part might alwayes ſee them before they came at her, and alſo (they) were rebuked and terrified by the man in ſuch ſort, as that they neuer came ruſhing or ouer raſhly vpon her, whereby ſhee might take any fright or ſodaine feare, but had imboldening and incouragement to ſtand or ſit ſtill in her owne defence. I haue knowne diuers coy <hi>Hawks</hi> my ſelf, that through good following and well manning in the field, haue proued very bold and ſtout, to reſiſt the raſh and haſtie encounters of very rough and vnruly <hi>Spaniels,</hi> that although through their owne hotneſſe, and alſo the lightneſſe of the Partridge, they haue cauſed her to carry it to ſome hedge or buſh out of the way,<note place="margin">It is the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Hawke to haue her prey in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate.</note> to ſhrowde her ſelfe from them, yet would neuer quite for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake it: neuertheleſſe, the ſame <hi>Hawke</hi> at her firſt entrance to the Couart, for want of the like go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, hath beene ſo ſuddenly feared and frighted, that ſhee would neuer after ſuffer any dogge in a thicke to come neare her, vnleſſe her Keeper were firſt in with her. And therefore to auoid this inconuenience and ill qualitie at the firſt, it is meete that ſhee be better manned, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed and gouerned, then formerly in the field
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:26902:44"/>
ſhee was, where moſt commonly ſhee might looke about her, and behold the dogges ſome ſpace before they came at her; and alſo (they) might ſee and know her, and therefore ſo much the better ſhunne and goe beſide her, for it is the raſh and ſudden ruſhing of the <hi>Spaniels</hi> vpon her, their ſight by meanes of the Couart being obſcured, and hauing an vncertaine and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne mixture of ſents in their noſes,<note place="margin">The Hawke and the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant.</note> and not diſcerning at an inſtant any difference betweene them, vnleſſe the bels giue warning, that breeds this vilde offence betweene thoſe friends, that ſhould be of one vnion.</p>
               <p>Therefore, if you will haue her made a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>Hawke,</hi> and to be bold, valiant,<note place="margin">The Hawke and the Spaniels.</note> and ventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous in the thicke woods, with the man, dogges and her game, as ſhee was in the plaine cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paine fields, you ought to make good choyce both of time, place, and dogges at her firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance; for the time, that would be early before the leafe doe ſtirre,<note place="margin">The time to enter the Hawke.</note> for then the Feſant flyes not farre: alſo afterwards, the nature of them is to forſake the yong ſhootes and ſmall groues, and draw to the high and thickeſt woods: alſo when the leafe doth fall, it is hard to reteriue with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny or few dogges, and thoſe you ſhall vſe in number would be but few, and alſo very eaſie to be commanded.</p>
               <p>Then when you haue made good choyce of your place to flye your <hi>Hawke</hi> in, and that you haue let her goe vnto her flight, you muſt bee
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:26902:45"/>
ſure to command your dogges behinde you,<note place="margin">Beware of the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niels.</note> vntill you haue found her; then if ſhee haue kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it, you haue your deſire; if not, and that you chance to finde her on the ground, as it may wel be you may, for many of them at the firſt ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring will bee very hot and eager of that ſport,<note place="margin">It ſhewes her true loue.</note> and oftentimes ſeeking for it on the ground: but if there bee any tree neare-hand, that ſhee may well ſee from it, put her vp into the ſame, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe keepe her on your fiſt, and beate for it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; then if ſhee doe flye and kill it, you muſt be ſure to make ſtay of the dogges vntill you haue directly found her: which being done, you ſhall get conueniently and gently in to her, and if you diſlike the place for the vneaſineſſe or thickneſſe,<note place="margin">Let the Hawke haue no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courageme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t at the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring.</note> you ſhall remooue her gently, and draw her into a more open place, where ſhe may with more eaſe quietly enioy her prey, and there ſuffer her to plume and take her pleaſure on it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while; then call your dogs vnto you, and walke and ſtirre gently about her, with ſome moderate ruſling and buſling in the buſhes, the better to acquaint her with the ſame noiſe: then when you ſee it conuenient, ſtoope to her on your knees, and rending the chappes, giue her bloud in the throate, whereas it will iſſue plentifully, to her great content; then paring the hard braine-pan from the reſt, and couering the bodie with your hat,<note place="margin">Good obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation for the yong ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </note> giue her the head in her foot to eate on the ground; and hauing your <hi>Spaniels</hi> cloſe by you; when ſhee hath done, and beginneth to
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:26902:45"/>
looke about her, throw the Feſant, euen as it it were in their very mouthes, that ſhe may (to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with ſome words of rebuke from your ſelfe) make them giue way with feare vnto her, yet drawing them into her ſight againe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, ſo long as ſhee is on the ground, and while you make her ſupper readie: and when you ſee ſhee hath taken her ſufficient pleaſure, exchange (that) artificially with her, and let her eate it on the ground where the quarrie lay, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſeruing ſome little thing to take her to your fiſt withall; and then put on her hood, not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting to beſtow ſome reward on her after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, which ſhee will bee well pleaſed withall, and take it for a kinde concluſion at your hand, and will not be curious to ſhew it outwardly, in her behauiour vnto you, with feaking, ietting, rowſing, and ſuch like ioyous ſhewes and ſignes alſo of inward pleaſure and contentment.</p>
               <p>Many a man, as ſoone as he hath taught his <hi>Hawke</hi> to draw and to come to his fiſt againe,<note place="margin">A great er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror or ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight.</note> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thinkes or conſiders of any other point be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing, but onely which is the next way to the wood, whereas he hopes to finde his game, and vnto that place he runnes or rides on headlong in hope of ſome good ſucceſſe; and when hee comes there, he may no doubt haue ſuch fortune, as to find his flight with ſpeed: yet all this while he remembers not that hee hath a ſtrange and vnacquainted <hi>Hawke,</hi> or a company of vnruly <hi>Spaniels,</hi> but he is certaine and knows right well
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:26902:46"/>
that he hath good ſtore, and alſo ſo many, as if there be but one Peſant in a reaſonable Couart, one or another of them will ſpring him, or put him vp, which is all he takes care for. And when he hath ſo done, and his <hi>Hawke</hi> hath flone, the next courſe he takes, is, he ſends his dogges be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,<note place="margin">A great fault.</note> himſelfe poſting them forward, with a lowde voyce, and crying, Goe ret, goe to the <hi>Hawke</hi> goe, as though they had as much wit as himſelfe, and could mannage all things ſo well as he: and then, Haue after, he cryes to himſelfe, and away he followes as faſt as hee can, in hope to finde ſome comfort; but when hee cometh neere to his <hi>Hawke,</hi> as hee deemes, he liſteneth, and looketh, and findeth her ſitting ſomething low in a tree, looking downeward, and prying to the ground in mournefull wiſe, as though ſhe were much diſpleaſed: at which ſight, withall, he is ſomething amazed, and then beginneth to looke further about him, and ſearcheth buſily and narrowly vnderneath, and round about her, miſtruſting that all things is not well; at laſt he findeth a mention of ill fortune, as feathers, ſtumpes of wings, legges or feete; but the whole bodie, that would haue cauſed him to trauell with a merrie heart homeward; and alſo haue ſerued for a chiefe and choice diſh at the table (that) is deuoured:<note place="margin">Why he ſent his dogges before him.</note> then he beginneth to ſtamp, and in an angrie mood to conceiue of his owne errour, and that there hath beene a hot skirmiſh betweene the <hi>Hawke,</hi> a poore Feſant, and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:26902:46"/>
company of vnmannerly tikes, wiſhing in his heart that the third part of them were all hanged: neuertheleſſe there is ſome comfort, for there ſits the <hi>Hawke</hi> ſtill, as well as euer ſhee was, ſhee hath by good fortune not loſt one member, ſhee was too wiſe, and more affraid then hurt, as it chanced; ſhee thought it not fit to bide the brunt at ſuch a battell, nor neuer wil thereafter, ſhee will hold it rather better for her the next time to bee gone, as ſoone as ſhee hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth eyther dogge or what elſe ſoeuer, but to ruſtle within a pole of her. And after this maner there hath beene many an excellent <hi>Hawke</hi> and dogge quite ſpoiled; for the <hi>Hawke</hi> will euer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, out of her feare, leaue her prey; and the hungrie and rauenous dogge hauing taſted of the ſweetneſſe thereof, will follow as faſt and cunningly to haue it, ſo that they are both ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and not one of them euer againe to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed,<note place="margin">A halter is fitteſt for a theefe.</note> without a ſpeedie courſe taken with a halter for the dogge; for that is meeteſt for a theefe, and ſuch dogges be alwayes called rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of <hi>Hawkes,</hi> and therefore are fitteſt to bee hanged: and for the <hi>Hawke,</hi> although her war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning hath been great, and her feare to truſt ſuch enemies to come neere her any more; yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe, with good vſage ſhee may be taught and made to forget it.</p>
               <p>And after that maner and faſhion, as hath bin heere formerly preſcribed, as,<note place="margin">A good ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation.</note> with a iudiciall Keeper, and diſcreete follower, faire flying, and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:26902:47"/>
two or three ſtanch and ſeruiceable <hi>Spaniels;</hi> and yet to make it more plaine vnto you, I ſay, hee that doth haſte on his dogges, before himſelfe, after any yong or ſtrange <hi>Hawke,</hi> it is done raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, vnaduiſedly, and without any diſcretion or iudgement, and hee taketh the cleane contrarie way; for it is his part, ſo ſoone as his <hi>Hawke</hi> is flone, to follow her as ſecretly as he may, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any noiſe, alſo as faſt as he can, vntill he hath found her; when as, if ſhee hath killed it, hee is there then cloſe by her, to guard and defend her, and may call for his <hi>Spaniels,</hi> and let them haue vnderſtanding what is befallen,<note place="margin">The Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niels muſt know what they hunt for.</note> that their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires may alſo be ſatisfied; and they may come ſo neere vnto her, as hee ſhall liſt himſelfe, and no nearer, ſo that there ſhall be no offence at all committed, but all parts well pleaſed: on the contrary, if ſhee haue miſſed her flight, yet there he is readie to call his <hi>Spaniels,</hi> and ſay, in ſtead of Go ret, Heere ret: and although they haue all loſt him in his race of running, yet hauing their hearing and ſmelling ſences, they will quickely bee with him; ſo that when they doe come and retetiue it, hee is readie to rate them, and gouerne all things to his owne liking: like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, if it be put to pearch, alſo there he is ready to rebuke the dogges at the fall: ſo that theſe courſes being well obſerued and followed, will make any <hi>Hawke,</hi> of reaſonable mettle, excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent. And when you haue made her neuer ſo good and perfect, yet in ſlacking of theſe things
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:26902:47"/>
ſhee will be as quickely marred;<note place="margin">There muſt be a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of carefull v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage.</note> for the beſt of that kinde that euer did flye, will continue in goodneſſe, and alter from the ſame, according as ſhee is ordered, flone, and followed.</p>
               <p>But all this while wee haue forgot the poore <hi>Hawke,</hi> ſhee is left vnconſidered of, let vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne backe and ſee what is become of her, ſhee was not wont to remoue or ſtirre from the mark or the man, but diligently to attend and waite his leiſure; and when he thought fit time to haue her, ſhee would come downe moſt willingly to his fiſt.</p>
               <p>But now he commeth to make triall of her, and after his accuſtomed maner, calleth for her,<note place="margin">The Hawke is angrie, and the Keeper not well pleaſed.</note> but hee perceiueth the caſe to bee altered with her; for ſhee no whit regardeth his call, ſhee is ſo angry, and hath beene ſo much offended, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in the ſame temper away ſhee goes, raling from one place to another, it may bee a mile or two before he can by any meanes come by her, nay it is ten to one but ſhee will kill a Hen or two before he can take her vp againe: which if ſhee doe ſo, I leaue it to the carefull <hi>Ostringer</hi> himſelfe, to teſtifie and conſider, what a trouble, with vexation of minde he is fallen into, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt knoweth not, neither can imagine, how or which way to remedie it. And therefore ſeeing that thoſe kinde of <hi>Hawkes</hi> of all other, are ſo ſubiect to take diſlikes, and learne il conditions, it behooues euery one that loues to keepe them, to be charie of them, and carefull, eſpecially at
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:26902:48"/>
their firſt making and entering; for if they bee then wel made, wel entred and imboldened with the man, the dogges and their game, it will bee a hard matter afterwards to beate them out of loue ſo much, but that they may with skill and paines taking, bee reclaimed and recouered againe, whereas otherwiſe there is little or no hope at all to be had of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">To imbol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the Hawke, and cauſe her take the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant from the pearch with cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage.</note>I haue yet omitted one courſe very requiſite to be conſidered of, and that ought to be taken, to teach the <hi>Goſhawke,</hi> and make her venter with boldneſſe to take the Feſant from the pearch, which ought to bee practiſed and brought to perfection: before you do offer her to fly there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, you ſhall prouide a yong Capon or browne Pullet, and take with you to the wood; when you are diſpoſed to cal her for her ſupper, and as ſhee is drawing and attending after you for the ſame, hauing a pole conuenient, proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded before for the ſame purpoſe, and fit oportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and place, you ſhal call your <hi>Spaniels</hi> about you to make them bay, and ſuddenly breaking the necke of the Poultrie, you ſhall at an inſtant lift it vpon a bough, ſo high as the <hi>Hawke</hi> may well haue ſight; there ſtirring it, and withall, as before, crying Abay, abay vnto her: at which noiſe, and as it were to ſee it flutter, no doubt but ſhee will come in and pull it downe; which if ſhe ſhall ſo doe,<note place="margin">Keepe the Dogges in awe.</note> be ſure that the dogges may, with ſome rebuke from your ſelf, giue her good leaue, &amp; make way for her deſcending; then ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:26902:48"/>
her to plume and take her pleaſure thereon, and nuzle her among the dogges, as you haue beene taught before, and giue her bloud in the throate, and let her bee well pleaſed and rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on it: and in vſing this courſe but a while, it will make her ſo bold and venturous, as that ſhe ſhall no ſooner ſee a Feſant goe to pearch, but ſhee wll as ſoone and ſuddenly haue him by the eares, and pull him downe.</p>
               <p>Alſo in vſing your art towards your <hi>Spaniels,</hi> with ſome words of threatening, and blowes with reaſon; it will alſo make them ſo vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and in ſuch ſubiection, as that you may boldly truſt them with her alone in your owne abſence,<note place="margin">Beware of ſtrange Dogges.</note> alwayes remembring there may be no ſtrangers amongſt them, for of that you ought to be moſt carefull at all times; for one ſtrange and vnruly dogge will put forward the beſt that be, and cauſe them to offend; and the <hi>Hawke</hi> alſo will ſuddenly know him, and giue way with feare vnto him, ſo that he is ſufficient to marre the reſt, and the <hi>Hawke</hi> alſo: yet there be many men that neuer once thinketh or conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth of what dogges it is meete they ſhould <hi>Hawke</hi> withall, or ſuffer to hunt amongſt their owne that they haue had proofe on, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to bee ſtanch and good: but certainely hee, whoſoeuer hee be, hath not neede to take more care for any thing whatſoeuer belonging to his arte, then for that one thing; for three or foure good dogges that be ſtanch, and knoweth what
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:26902:49"/>
they ſhould doe, is at all times better then three or foure couple that be vnruly and riotous, as you may well vnderſtand, if you wil but marke; when you ſhall ſuffer but one more to hunt with them, you ſhall ſee when as they will range and beate of very purpoſe quietly and cunningly for the Feſant, and chalenge of no other thing: the other dogge will hunt euery thing, or any thing that he firſt findeth; and not onely doe ſo, but alſo draw the other vnto him, and cauſe them to bawke the Feſant,<note place="margin">A great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenience.</note> that otherwiſe they would moſt certainly haue found. If this be ſo, as moſt true it is, then doe but conſider what many ſuch may doe: as alſo I doe not deny, but that they may all chance to ſpring together; yet if it fall out that they doe meete at a bay, they will not onely themſelues be readie to pull the <hi>Hawke</hi> in peeces,<note place="margin">An excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t diſh.</note> but alſo tempt the other, and ſet on them to doe the like, or at leaſt to deuoure the Feſant; that otherwiſe would neuer of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues haue any whit offended.</p>
               <p>Thus hauing according to this one rule and preſcription, taught your <hi>Hawke</hi> this neceſſary and needfull leſſon, you may bee bold to ſhew her the wilde Feſant, when you finde it conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, and ſhee will be in all points readie to flye at him, and couragiouſly to make ſeazure, and prey vpon him without any feare.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Enter her firſt to the Cocke,</note>Alſo you muſt be carefull to enter her firſt to the Cocke, for as I haue often told you, all <hi>Hawkes</hi> be not alike in their diſpoſition, but are
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:26902:49"/>
of contrary natures,<note place="margin">Seeke out the nature of the Hawke.</note> and therefore will require great and diligent attendance, and skill to finde out their properties: and the ſame being perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowne, you may order your <hi>Hawke</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly; whereas otherwiſe you ſhall commit many errors, and ſeldome make a good <hi>Hawke.</hi> Therefore, if you finde her at firſt to incounter boldly with him, you neede not doubt, being well pleaſed and blouded on him, afterward to let her take her pleaſure and chance in drawing, and to fly at what riſeth firſt, be it Cock or Hen. Contrariwiſe, if you perceiue her to be fearefull and cowardly, as not to buckle and kill him boldly, then with two or three dayes reſt, and hard waſhed feede, prepare her ſtomack ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and put her to him againe, and leaue not off your paines and practiſe, vntill you haue made her to flye at him ſpiritfully, and kill him as boldly.</p>
               <p>Some man before he hath vſed any manner of meanes,<note place="margin">Great indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion.</note> whereby hee may geſſe or iudge of her, or what ſpirit or mettle is in her, will at very firſt put her vp to draw the Couart, thinking thereby to giue her ſome vantage towards her firſt entring: but many times hee is deceiued in his expectation, for the Henne Feſant is as eaſily found as the Cocke; and the verieſt daſtard of that kinde will ſeldome refuſe to flye at her,<note place="margin">The verieſt daſtard wil kill the Hen Feſant.</note> and alſo to kill her, and then being well blouded withall, her Keeper thinkes he hath done well, and his minde is pleaſed: but it is not ſo, for of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:26902:50"/>
it falleth out, that afterward with all the arte and skill he hath, he ſhall neuer force her flye the Cocke againe.</p>
               <p>Thus with theſe raſh and haſtie courſes, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Hawkes</hi> are quickly ſpoyled, which although at firſt they haue not ſo much mettle and ſpirit, with boldneſſe appearing in them, neither by nature, as many other <hi>Hawkes</hi> haue; yet with good conſideration of the ſame, and the carefull paines and skill of their Keeper, with due time adioined,<note place="margin">Worthy of commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> they may be made very good <hi>Hawkes:</hi> and hee thereby ſhall iuſtly deſerue more prayſe and commendations for the perfect making of one ſuch <hi>Hawke,</hi> then of ten other, that will at firſt out of their owne ſpirit and mettle flye, and make themſelues with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, in a manner, any aſſiſtance at all from their Keeper.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:26902:50"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> A note worthy of obſeruation for the imboldening of any <hi>Hawke,</hi> that hath beene rebuked or diſcouraged by the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niels.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Henſoeuer in your recreation and ſporting abroad with your <hi>Hawke,</hi> it ſhal be your happe to meete with ſuch a Feſant, as will not, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe is not able to riſe againe after it hath beene hard flone, but ſhall be there taken on the ground betweene the dogges and your ſelfe; doe not then by my aduice, ſeeke for any open or plaine place to take your <hi>Hawke</hi> downe vpon, but otherwiſe and immediatly it ſhall be your beſt courſe, to rebuke the dogges out of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:26902:51"/>
the way,<note place="margin">This order will preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imbolden her.</note> and withall to throw the Feſant vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loft vnto her, vſing your voyce withall, and there let her truſſe it
<figure>
                     <head>GOSHAWKE.</head>
                  </figure>
and fall with it to the ground, and if ſhee ſhall chaunce, through any feare or other occaſion, to loſe or let it goe by the way, as often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it commeth ſo to paſſe; yet let her haue it againe, or elſe neuer to enioy it any other way, vntill ſhee will boldly doe the ſame without any feare at all, and then draw in your dogges about her, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint them wel together; and for want of a Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, vſe her oftentimes after this matter to take her downe with a pullet, amongſt, or neere vnto the <hi>Spaniels,</hi> with ſuch care, as that they may not any way offend her in the fall; and before it be long, this order will ſo well imbolden her with the fal, and encourage her to hold amongſt the dogges againe, as that ſhee will quite forget all former vnkindneſſes offered vnto her, and truſſe her prey againe boldly, without any feare at all, being euermore aſſured, that vpon any ſuch occaſion, the ſtomacke may bee ſharpe in the higheſt degree, for that will ſharpen alſo her tallants, and cauſe her to hold faſt indeed. And without that one thing, there is no other courſe
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:26902:51"/>
to be taken, or meanes to bee vſed with her, for ſhee will neuer be ſubiect to your will.</p>
               <p>Alſo to vſe your yong <hi>Hawke</hi> at her firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance after the ſame manner, it will perfectly encourage her to the like, whenſoeuer ſhee ſhall haue occaſion, without any manner of feare at all; for it is only at the firſt entring, being not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted, the falling to the ground or buſhes, neare vnto men or horſes, and the <hi>Spaniels</hi> bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with their ſeuerall noyſes, that doth terrifie her, and oftentimes after cauſeth the loſſe of prey from her foote: for of all <hi>Hawkes,</hi> ſhee is the moſt nice and choyce, and therfore will aske and require more skill and attendance at her firſt making, then any other whatſoeuer; and for want of ſuch neceſſarie and iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall conſiderations and courſes, at that time, there hath bin many an excellent <hi>Hawke</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by her Keeper, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhee haue been halfe made.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:26902:52"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi> The <hi>Haggart Goſhawke</hi> in particular.</head>
               <figure>
                  <head>• THE HAGGARD FAVLCON IN OPEM ME COPIA FECIT</head>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hus farre haue I written and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed of the <hi>Goſhawke</hi> in generall, and ſhewed that of all other kinds, ſhee is the wildeſt and moſt ſtoute <hi>Hawke,</hi> and that it is more difficult and hard at the firſt to draw her into true ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection, and familiaritie with the man, then any other whatſoeuer; and that it is altogether in
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:26902:52"/>
vaine at that time to commit her into the cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die or keeping of any yong or vnexperienced Keeper, that is not able through his iudgement and skill, to order her as ſhee ought to be.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>FAVLCON 1. <hi>booke.</hi>
                  </head>
               </figure>
               <p>Shee is the abſolute wildeſt <hi>Hawke</hi> of all, and will therefore deſerue much more labour and skill in her reclaiming and perfect making, then any of the other: and therefore there ought to be had ſo much the greater care and attendance on her, with ſuch or the like preparation againſt the time you intend to make her gentle, as I haue before preſcribed vnto you.</p>
               <p>For whereas it is an vſuall courſe with moſt men vpon the receit of ſuch a <hi>Hawke</hi> from the Cage, ſuddenly to make her gentle, by peppe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, watching, and other ſuch like accuſtomed vſes, without any former conſideration or ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, how vnfit her bodie may bee, to bee ſo ſuddenly ſtriuen withall and ouer-heat with
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:26902:53"/>
holding and turmoiling in the hot water, that hath been reſted, and therefore moſt like is char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and ouercharged with groſſe imperfect fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and other ſuch like humors, which being ſo ſuddenly ſtirred and diſperſed by immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and haſtie dealing, may well hazzard her life; and for certaine many <hi>Hawkes</hi> haue beene loſt that way.</p>
               <p>Wherefore I would haue you call to minde what order I haue formerly preſcribed for ſuch a <hi>Hawke;</hi> and that being well effected, then may you goe forward boldly after the ſame manner, and ſee there be no ſparing of paines in carrying and other neceſſary courſes, vntill you well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue by all ſignes of her good behauiour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, that ſhee is gentle and well reclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</p>
               <p>Further, as touching her dyet, feeding, calling or other manner of outward or inward dealing, vntill ſhee be readie to flye; I ſhall not neede to meddle withall, becauſe I haue before ſo plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſſed the ſame, only I would haue you to obſerue this one note; which is, that theſe kind of <hi>Hawkes</hi> being wilde, doe all naturally loue to feed on their prey in couart places, as where they may not be diſcried or ſeene, by other ſuch birds of the ayre as loueth them not.</p>
               <p>Alſo, and otherwiſe being reclaimed by the man, whenſoeuer they doe take it in any cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paine or plaine place, they will doe the like, and carry it to the next place of harbor, to be ſhrou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:26902:53"/>
or ſhadowed there; ſo much and ſo often they haue beene not onely taught, but alſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced vnto it,<note place="margin">Crowes Kites, and all other ſuch ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine.</note> being abroad and ſhifting continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally amongſt their enemies, that would, but that they dare not, perſecute them for their vigour and crueltie, ſuch is their malice towards them; and therefore neuertheleſſe, will not ceaſe with open crie to raile and wonder at them while that they may be ſeene, and oftentimes cauſeth them to forſake their prey.</p>
               <p>In this regard, when any one of theſe <hi>Hawkes</hi> hath after this manner ſafely ſhrowded her ſelfe, ſhee will ſit very cloſe, and preſently fall to fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: which euill courſe ſhee will continually hold,<note place="margin">A great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenience.</note> to the great trouble and vexation of her Keeper, vnleſſe ſhee be with great care and skill well reclaimed from the ſame.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, during the time of her calling, it behoueth you to take this courſe with her, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though you doe call and draw her by your chir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and whiſtle, along after you, thorow the thicke and couart places, the which is meete you ſhould doe; yet doe not there take her to your fiſt to be fully ſatisfied, but let her ſtill attend and waite on you, vntill you come to ſome plaine conuenient place, and there entertaine her in the beſt manner to the fiſt, and let her feede a little thereon; then put to her leaſe, and let her eate the reſidue on the ground cloſe by you, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing reſerued ſome ſtumpe or other ſuch thing, take her to your fiſt againe, and ſo conclude with
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:26902:54"/>
her for that time. Alſo forget not, but that you doe ſtoope gently to her on your knee, and quietly and ſoftly conuey ſome bittes vnſeene farre off vnto her, that you giue her no cauſe of vnquietneſſe, as to ſtrike at your hand with her tallants: for thoſe kinde of <hi>Hawkes</hi> will not endure to haue any ſuch thing openly ſhewed, or offered vnto them; they will bee ſo ſharpely diſpoſed and eager at the ſight of it, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there ought to bee much heede taken by the man in his behauiour towards them, and neatneſſe vſed, with handſome and cleanely conueyances in all his outward dealings.</p>
               <p>This courſe being well perfected with quiet and gentle vſage euery day, ſo long as you doe call her, will ſo imbolden her, and worke all manner of feare out of her, as that ſhee will neuer after haue any deſire to carry any thing from you: ſhee will grow ſo farre in loue, and bee familiar with you; but will bee well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and account her ſelfe ſafely ſhrowded when ſhee hath your company, and is cloſe by you.</p>
               <p>Now when you haue after this manner thus kindly reclaimed and framed her to your will, it will bee good time to enter her to the field, and for that I haue before ſo plainly ſet downe and preſcribed the order and manner how and which way to accompliſh the ſame, I will omit to ſpeake any more of that point, and proceed onwards to the next.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:26902:54"/>When as ſhee ſhall come to kill Partridge, then as I haue formerly aduiſed, you muſt bee ſure to get gently in to her, hauing before pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided her dinner or ſupper readie dreſſed; and as ſhee ſitteth on the Partridge, beſtow the ſame on her in bits,<note place="margin">Shee would be pleaſed alwayes from your hand.</note> with neate and handſome conueyance, which will prolong her time in pluming, and ſtay the ſharpneſſe of her appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite and deſire to feede, which is not fitte ſhee ſhould doe; for it would cauſe her to loue that better they your ſelfe, and to bee loath and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing afterwards at any time to bee bereaued of it,<note place="margin">In ſome thicke co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uart.</note> and thereby will take occaſion to carrie it from you, hoping to enioy it to her ſelfe more ſecret and quietly; whereas otherwiſe this courſe will ſo pleaſe her, and draw her loue ſo certaine to you, as that ſhee will neuer after offer to carrie one feather from you.</p>
               <p>Alſo, all this while giue no bloud at all, but with ſome reuerſion take her to your fiſt againe, and there content her, and before it be long, ſhee will bee ſo conſtantly wonne and reclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to your will, as that ſhee will neuer co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet or deſire to carrie her prey any whit from the place where ſhee taketh it;<note place="margin">I ſpeak this by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and on my credite.</note> neyther vvill ſhee euer breake it, ſo long as there is one fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther left on it, but ſtill attend for your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and to haue a reward onely at your hand. And therefore, if you may chooſe, let her ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer take any bloud her ſelfe, but when you haue well nuzled and inured her herein, and that
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:26902:55"/>
you doe at any time after finde her with a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridge in her foote: then after good time ſpent in pluming, take off the head and necke, and giue it vnto her with the moſt part of her ſupper together; which when ſhee hath eaten, and doth looke about her, take her to your fiſt, and ſo conclude with her.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVIII.</hi> That the <hi>Hawke</hi> being well entred, and in loue with Partridge, ought not to be flone to the Couart at all.</head>
               <figure/>
               <figure/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a rare thing to haue a <hi>Hawke</hi> of this kind to be good to the field and couart both; and therefore if you perceiue your yong <hi>Hawke</hi> at her firſt making to be nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:26902:55"/>
and wight of her wings, and alſo to ſet her loue on the Partridge, and thereon to take de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, which will eaſily bee perceiued by her eager and fierce flying, with the ioy ſhee will take in it, and iocond buſineſſe ſhee will haue with it, when ſhe hath the Partridge in her foot: then this being well approued, it were great pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to let her ſee the Feſant at any time, or at leaſt to vſe her to that kinde of game or manner of flight:<note place="margin">He is a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and tempting bird.</note> for being a <hi>Hawke</hi> ſo eager and greedie of her prey, as they all in their owne natures bee, will deſire and more delight a ſhort flight, and to haue it ſpeedie, then otherwiſe to couet or bee willing to purſue it, and hold out at length; which ſhee ſhall bee conſtrained to doe, if ſhee wil haue the mounting and ſtyning Partridge to be at her command: and for the Feſant, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that he is a fowle in ſhew and other appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, farre greater then the other: hee ſeemeth alſo in the manner of his flight, to be ſo much the more vnweildie and heauie, and flyeth not ſo farre as the Partridge doth; all which are great prouocations, and tempteth the <hi>Hawke</hi> to flye couragiouſly with more eagerneſſe and ſpiritfull aſſurance to enioy him, then the other;<note place="margin">The Feſant.</note> therefore his flght is of force, and ſufficient to withdraw her loue cleane away, although ſhee hath beene otherwiſe well entred, inured, and blouded before: for the beſt <hi>Hawke</hi> of that kind, being wilde, and at her owne diſpoſing, coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not, if they may chooſe, to flye farre after
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:26902:56"/>
the thing ſhee chiefely deſireth to prey vpon,<note place="margin">The true nature of the Hawke.</note> but moſt commonly vſeth her policie by ſudden and cunning ſtealing vpon the ſame, and what ſhee can winne after that manner ſooneſt, and with leaſt paines, the ſame ſhee moſt delighteth in; by which appeareth, when we haue them in our owne cuſtodie and keeping, the beſt of them all may bee made bad enough through want of skill and knowledge, with other careleſſe vſage in her Keeper.</p>
               <p>Contrariwiſe, who hath a true care and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding in the arte hee profeſſeth, may through his labour and pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full practiſe, make one of farre more baſer mettle to doe him right good ſeruice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:26902:56"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIX.</hi> To teach the <hi>Goſhawke</hi> to flye to the Wilde-ducke or Mallard, that frequenteth the ponds or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate pittes; which is a good ſport, and a good prey when it is taken.</head>
               <figure>
                  <head>GOSHAWKE.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S you know right well, in moſt Countries there bee many odde pondes that ſtand in cloſe and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret places, as amongſt ſhrubbes, or buſhes, or otherwiſe inuironed with wood growing vpward, that hideth and obſcureth the water from the fight and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of any trauellers that paſſeth to and fro, vnleſſe they be ſuch as perfectly knoweth them, or otherwiſe, thoſe that by chance doth light
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:26902:57"/>
vpon them.<note place="margin">The nature of the fowle</note> In theſe kinde of pooles the Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lard, with the Duckes his louing companions, doth take great delight and pleaſure, there to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and ſolace themſelues priuately together, to their great contentment and ſafe aſſurance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any enemy, that ſhall by ſtealth draw neare to betray them.</p>
               <p>Now whereas I haue formerly deliuered my opinion herein, that there is no <hi>Hawke</hi> of this kinde, in her wildneſſe, but is able to ſhift for her ſelfe ſufficiently, and kill ſundrie kindes of prey; and afterward being reclaimed: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then ſhould not the man by his art, cauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them to doe the like for him? ſo that by this reaſon there is no excuſe to be made for him that ſhall haue one of them in his hand a long time, to practiſe and worke vpon, and ſhal in the end ſay ſhee is a buzzard; ſhee is of a bad carry, he can make her do nothing at all. To the which I anſwere, that ſuch a one is more fit for ſome other calling, then to beare the title or name of eyther <hi>Falconer</hi> or <hi>Ostringer;</hi> for if ſhee may be made but to kill meate for other <hi>Hawkes,</hi> ſhee is well worthy of her owne, and there is ſome pleaſure in it beſides; and for ſuch a one as will neither be forced by the arte and induſtry of her Keeper, to kill the Partridge or Feſant, I wil here ſhew how ſhee may bee made not onely to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey for her owne or other <hi>Hawkes</hi> dyet, but alſo to giue good ſatisfaction and content to her Keeper: and to accompliſh and bring the ſame
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:26902:57"/>
to perfection, you muſt obſerue well this order following.</p>
               <p>When your <hi>Hawke</hi> is readie in all points to be flone, you muſt prouide you of three or foure hand-fowle, if they bee not wilde, yet bee ſure they may bee of the ſame colour, or as neare as you can, the which you ſhall let your <hi>Hawke</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly flye at, and foote out of ones hand one after another, day after day, and let her plume and be well rewarded of them; and when you perceiue that ſhee will doe thus with an eager and hot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, as no doubt, but ſhee will very quickly doe in the higheſt degree of loue towards them; then you muſt prouide you of a fowle or two more, as you may eaſily doe, and alſo that will flye ſo farre as you ſhall haue neede: and when you purpoſe to goe abroad againe with your <hi>Hawke,</hi> ſend one before you with a fowle, and alſo your directions, to ſome cloſe place of plumpe of buſhes, where he may be very ſafely ſhrowded from your ſelfe, and alſo the ſight of the <hi>Hawke;</hi> then ſhall you follow after your ſelfe with her rightly prepared,<note place="margin">Spurres to pricke her forward.</note> with her ſtomacke ſharpely edged for her prey: and when you come there cloſe by the brimme or border of the thicket or fore-pointed harbour, and hauing your <hi>Hawke</hi> readie for a ſudden and delightfull encounter, you ſhall ſtrike hard on the buſhes with your pole, at which fore-knowne warning, the ſtill couched meſſenger, ſhall with all his might toſſe the fowle aloft vpright; which if ſhee doe with
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:26902:58"/>
courage take, an excellent catch-Ducke ſhee will make.</p>
               <p>Then after this you may boldly goe to the ponds or pits, where the wilde fowle lies, and as before ſaid, creepe as neere as you may, holding your <hi>Hawke</hi> as high as you can, and with your pole beate vp the fowle, when as they ſhall no ſooner beginne to riſe, but ſhee will be as readie at the ſudden ſowce to pull one of them backe againe; which if ſhee doe ſo, bee ſure to croſſe the wings of it, and let her take her pleaſure thereon in pluming, and bee rewarded of the ſame, and after that ſhe will not miſſe one flight that ſhee ſhall be flone to after that manner: alſo it will not be amiſſe to haue a dogge alwayes with you, for ſometimes after the <hi>Hawke</hi> is well acquainted with the ſport, ſhee will bee ſo nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and quicke at the catch, that they will fall both into the water together, and by that meanes the fowle may goe to plunge, ſo that then the dog may and will be readie to doe you good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, wherby neuertheleſſe the <hi>Hawke</hi> may be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:26902:58"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XX.</hi> To flye to the Wilde-gooſe or Hearon, to the Rooke, the Mew, or any other ſuch ſhort flight, which are to be killed at the ſudden ſowce, by the policie of the <hi>Hawke</hi> that is not ſwift of her wing to take them otherwiſe</head>
               <figure>
                  <head>• THE HAGGARD FAVLCON IN OPEM ME COPIA FECIT</head>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He moſt <hi>Hawkes</hi> of this kinde, doth naturally loue to prey vpon any of theſe things that I haue heere named, and therefore it is ſo much the eaſier to make one of them by arte to flye thereunto:
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:26902:59"/>
neuertheleſſe, on this conſideration, that they in their wildeneſſe doe not altogether diſpoſe themſelues towards any one particular thing of them; nor ſettle their loues or deſire onely on them, nor no more then they doe of the reſt, or many other things that they alſo doe vſe to prey vpon, as well as they: therefore if you will haue one of them to doe you ſeruice therein, and to be conſtant in her flight thereunto, you muſt not vſe her raſhly, as truſting wholly in her owne naturall diſpoſition, or loue to the thing you would haue her to flye vnto.<note place="margin">Her owne loue.</note> But you muſt giue a further addition and aſſiſtance to the ſame, by your owne arte and cunning practiſe, extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily to encreaſe and make it perfect withall; for there is no man of any vnderſtanding, that hath a buſineſſe of any importance to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh, that will goe raſhly about the ſame, and without any conſideration,<note place="margin">An additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</note> thinke euen ſo to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect it, but he will bethinke himſelfe better of it, and caſt which is the beſt way, and what courſe is fitteſt for him to take in it; and then hee will arme and prepare himſelfe with diſcretion, to put the ſame in practiſe and execution; and no doubt, but then hee ſhall haue all things goe to his liking, and alſo good ſucceſſe in the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p>Euen ſo likewiſe when you haue taught your <hi>Hawke</hi> to goe, and to come againe vnto your fiſt, and that as you thinke ſhee is readie in all points to be flone, yet it is not fit that then you
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:26902:59"/>
goe with purpoſe to flye her, or to force her flye at what you liſt, or would haue her to kill: but you muſt further conſider what kinde of things ſuch a <hi>Hawke</hi> in her wildeneſſe doth vſe to prey and liue vpon, and is poſſible for the man by his arte to make her vnto.</p>
               <p>Then all this being well conſidered and thought on, you may make your choice, as of which one particular thing you would haue her moſt addicted vnto, and to loue better then the reſt, for your owne delight and pleaſure; ſo as if you thinke well euen of the Rooke, a fowle, which although there is not much worth in the thing it ſelfe, yet it will ſerue well for her owne or other <hi>Hawkes</hi> dyet: and alſo through this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and obſeruation, you may bee inſtructed how to make her to other things of more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance and valew, as to any of thoſe other things I haue formerly named.</p>
               <p>Therefore when you haue your <hi>Hawke</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die in all points to flye, you muſt prouide you of ſome liue traynes, the which you may eaſily doe, eyther in Sommer or Winter; then when you would enter your <hi>Hawke,</hi> let one of them haue the wing pulled or cut; and when you come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the field in ſome greene place or ſlade, let the ſame bee placed or ſette downe there on the ground, and retire backe your ſelfe, with your <hi>Hawke,</hi> ſome fortie paces from it, or as you ſhall ſee cauſe, for you may draw neere vnto it againe at your owne pleaſure; then take off her Hood,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:26902:60"/>
that ſhee may looke round about her, and finde where the traine is very like, buſily diſpoſed, as ſtirring, walking, or ſuch like: then if ſhee doe flye to it, and take it, let her plume and bee well rewarded on it: and after this manner you muſt order her, vntill ſhee will finde the traine readily as it is walking, ſo farre off as ſhee may well ſee it, and goe as readily and take it after that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion.</p>
               <p>Then the next time you intend to walke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, let your traine be a flyer, and placed at one end of a long creance, with a peg put ſlightly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ground, only to ſtay it, and no more, ſome yard or two from the end, whereunto the traine is faſtened; and at the other end of the creance a marke ſet whereby you may readily find it: then draw towards it,<note place="margin">The traine.</note> and vnhood your <hi>Hawke,</hi> that ſhee may ſee it; and when ſhee hath found it, and is gone from the fiſt well towards it, be ſure to pull vp the peg, that when the traine ſhall ſee her well neare come at it, it may haue ſome li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie to flye, although it bee but neuer ſo little before ſhee doe take it.</p>
               <p>Thus if you can after this manner in your diſcretion, let her kill ſome two or three more, and ſo order the matter with the creance, that when the <hi>Hawke</hi> ſhal be almoſt at it, euen then it may haue ſome reaſonable ſcope to riſe before ſhee can take it; it will ſo nuzzell her, as that ſhee wil not after miſſe the wilde Rooke or any other thing you ſhall after this manner make her vnto.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>FAVLCON 1. <hi>booke.</hi>
                  </head>
               </figure>
               <p>There be many of theſe <hi>Hawkes</hi> that be very large and ſtrong, and withall as heauie and ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſh of their wings, and therefore will neuer hold out to any of the long flights, but altogether do ſhift and get their prey by ſubtiltie and craft; neuertheleſſe the moſt of them are very hardie to ſeize on any thing. And theſe be they that are moſt fit to be made and taught to flye to theſe ſhort and great flights, and to catch at the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſowce; which they will very quickly learne to doe with your owne arte and aſſiſtance, becauſe their owne nature doth very much di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and leade them e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:26902:61"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXI.</hi> Of the <hi>Sparhawke.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>SPAROWHAWKE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſidering that at firſt it was my ſpeciall purpoſe to treate of ſhort-winged <hi>Hawkes;</hi> and alſo in my proceeding, with them to ioyne ſome others, the which I haue not forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to ſpeake of: ſo alſo let me bee no more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindfull of one demie creature, that for her ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and mettle, is well worthy to martch in the beſt company, and therein is nothing inferiour: The <hi>Sparhawke</hi> I meane, which I haue knowne to be of great worth and eſtimation, for the well performing her ſeruice, with great delight and pleaſure extended to her Keeper; as by her ſpirit
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:26902:62"/>
and policie to take any thing ſhee ſhall bee made to, and the manner how, as at the firſt ſight of the thing wherewithal ſhe intendeth to incoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to behold how, and in what maner ſhe firſt falleth flat to the fiſt, ſhewing thereby her imbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cillitie and vnableneſſe of bodie, for ſuch vne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall matches: withall, as it were with diſcretion and deliberation, findeth her beſt aduantage; and ſo expecting the ſpeedie preſence of her Keeper, and his kinde aſſiſtance in the skirmiſh, away ſhee goeth couragiouſly, cloſe by the ground and nimbly, to the wilde Crow, the Rooke, the Mewe, the Lapwing, the Ringdoue, the Houſedoue on the lands, the Pie-annit, the brauing and chattering laye; and there is none of all theſe fowles, beſides ſome others that I haue omitted, but after this manner ſhee will make ſubiect to her command, and yeeld to the mercie of her ſharpe and piercing tallants. And for the Partridge, I haue likewiſe knowne her as great a commander, and to hold out, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue all the Sommer time, as well as any other <hi>Hawkes</hi> would doe. And now on the contrarie (ſhee) poore prettie Birde, is of no requeſt or reckoning at all, but is almoſt quite forgotten of all men: for the which they are much to blame vndoubtedly; for by experience, I know, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that ſeaſon, there is no better <hi>Hawke</hi> then ſhee, if ſhee be kept as ſhee ought to bee, high, luſtie, and ſtrong: but in theſe dayes the yong man hath ſo deepely addicted himſelfe to ſloath
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:26902:62"/>
and idleneſſe, with drowſie ſluggiſhneſſe, and other wandering mutabilities, as that he had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dye then to meddle with a <hi>Hawke</hi> that will require either labour or attendance early or late, or any other time of the day, but will reclaime and make their <hi>Hawkes</hi> gentle with bating and hanging by the heeles, which is the cauſe, and for want of better guiding, that theſe poore ſilly birds be not able to performe their ſeruice, which otherwiſe they would doe; for you muſt vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand they be all but wretches, of little and ſmall ſtrength; and to haue any part of that dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed or taken away, it is not poſſible they ſhould be able to maintaine their flight: but otherwiſe, to bee ſtrongly kept in the Hood, and alwayes flone from the ſame, ſhee is a moſt excellent <hi>Hawke,</hi> and will kill more Partridge in one day, then the beſt long-winged <hi>Hawke</hi> will doe in two; and ſhee is for euery place, you need make no difference of thicke or thinne. And for her dyet, that would be of the daintieſt meate you can get, vnleſſe in other times of reſt, and alſo then, not forgetting to waſh it well and drie it againe, eſpecially if ſhee bee mued: likewiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſhee is to flye, ſhee muſt bee prepared af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſame manner, with a ſhort cut to put a perfect edge on her, and then ſhee will flye after the beſt manner; and no <hi>Hawke</hi> with more ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and mettle then ſhee. Alſo ſhee would not be flone in the morning, vnleſſe ſhee bee prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ouer-night with a ſhort and cleane ſupper
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:26902:63"/>
for the purpoſe, and then ſhee will flye for her owne reward, and content of her Keeper. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, you ought to haue alwayes a prettie box a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout you, full of freſh Butter, mixed with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Saffron and Sugarcandie, to giue with her meate now and then, or to eate out of the box; which ſhee will doe with great delight, and it will keepe her head euermore looſe, and in good temper, and alſo preuent the Cray, and keepe her proud and full of ſpirit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXII.</hi> Of the <hi>Lanner</hi> and <hi>Lanneret.</hi>
               </head>
               <figure>
                  <head>LANNER.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am now come to ſpeake of the <hi>Lanner</hi> and <hi>Lanneret,</hi> which although they bee a kinde of <hi>Hawkes,</hi> I neuer tooke much
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:26902:63"/>
delight in, yet I will ſhew you my opinion, and what otherwiſe I haue gathered by my little practiſe and obſeruation from them.</p>
               <p>Then firſt giue mee leaue to let you vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that in my obſeruation they are all by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and kinde, of a hard and dull diſpoſition, apt to doe little good of themſelues, nor other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, but what they are forcibly compelled to doe, by their Keepers ordering of them. And for the <hi>Lanner</hi> her ſelfe, in my life time I haue heard heere and there one of them that hath beene called or accounted good; but as one Swallow maketh no Sommer, ſo one particula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie concludeth no generalitie: alſo and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, the beſt good ſhewed by them at any time, in the little experience that I haue had of them, doth alwayes appeare without true delight, after a tedious and baſe toyling kinde of faſhion, and in my opinion farre vnfit to giue a Gentleman content in his ſport and recreation: and ſo I will ceaſe heere to ſpeake any more in generall, but eſpecially in diſcommendations of them, leſt I ſhould ſeeme offenſiue to any, or to daunt the yong <hi>Faulconer,</hi> or him that moſt of all for their ſowndes and long laſting, deſires to practiſe and be dealing with them: but what was it that I ſaid before? did I ſay that I would euen ſo leaue them? ſurely that were not well done of mee, I muſt needs confeſſe; and it ſhall goe hard neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, but I ſhall finde in my memorie ſome cauſe, wherefore I ſhould not altogether ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:26902:64"/>
ſake them, but rather to make ſome amends, it is otherwiſe meete I ſhould do ſomething in praiſe particularly of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIII.</hi> Of the <hi>Haggart Lanner.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>LANNER.</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the <hi>Eyas</hi> of this kinde exceedeth other <hi>Hawkes,</hi> towards their Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, in loue and gentleneſſe, euen ſo doth the <hi>Haggart</hi> of the ſame nature, as farre ſurpaſſe the reſt in exceeding wildeneſſe, and are very hard to be reclaimed; and therefore whoſe hap it ſhal be to meet with any of them, he muſt take extraordinarie time and paines to make them gentle; and alſo all the luring time the like
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:26902:64"/>
courſe muſt be vſed, and ſee that ſhee be taught and made to come perfectly to the Lure, onely garniſhed with hard waſhed meate, and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides ſhee may receiue the better part of her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in bittes at your hands; euen as you were to order the <hi>Faulcon:</hi> and afterwards during her trayning, there muſt bee much time taken, and otherwiſe the very ſelfe ſame ordering and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward manner of dealing, that I haue formerly appointed for the <hi>Haggart Faulcon,</hi> in any other booke of Hawking: ſo that it were but in vaine for mee to ſet downe any other particular pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription; and no doubt, but with ſuch well go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerning, and good time taken, they may make good <hi>Hawkes:</hi> it was neuer my happe, to my remembrance, to ſee any more then one Caſt of them, and they neuer came to any perfection, but euen were deſtroyed through their owne coyneſſe, and their Keepers ouer much haſte and raſhneſſe, and alſo his hard dealing in their diet, and with too much ſtoaning: and ſo I will ceaſe to ſay any more of them, but will proceed to the other of the ſame kind.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:26902:65"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIIII.</hi> Of the <hi>Ramage Lanner</hi> to the Field.</head>
               <figure>
                  <head>LANNER.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here be many of theſe <hi>Hawkes</hi> that hath reaſonable ſpirits and mettle remaining in them, and doth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times proue good <hi>Hawkes,</hi> when it is their happes to light into their hands that hath iudgement and knowledge to reclaime them.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>FAVLCON 1. <hi>booke.</hi>
                  </head>
               </figure>
               <p>On the contrarie part, the <hi>Lanner,</hi> as ſhee is nothing inferiour to the other in ramage and wildeneſſe, ſo is ſhee more hard of ward and of a farre more ſtrong and ſound conſtitution, and yet will not bee drawne by any gentle dealing to doe any thing, or to bee pleaſing to the man, but will euermore deſerue to haue ſpurres put to her dull diſpoſition, to pricke her forcibly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:26902:66"/>
to performe her dutie; and yet when you haue done the beſt you can, as manned her, lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, trayned and ſtayed her; all which to effect, I can preſcribe no better courſe then the very ſame that I haue ſpoken of, or taught in my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Booke, for the <hi>Haggart Faulcon</hi> onely, and excepting her dyet, for that muſt be conſidered of, with hard waſhed meate and ſtones, more or leſſe, as you ſhall finde her naturall incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; for you muſt vnderſtand that they are not all alike, but doe differ as much as others doe; and therefore ought to be regarded there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
               <p>Now when you haue thus farre foorth effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted your deſire, yet haue you not well conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with her, vnleſſe you bee mindfull of this one thing, and alſo haue well perfected the ſame; which is, that through your paines and skilfull practiſe you doe well ſtay her, and by your arte alſo reſtraine her from dragging or carrying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing from you; the which ill qualitie, there is no one <hi>Hawke</hi> more ſubiect vnto then ſhee.</p>
               <p>Therefore, to preuent the ſame; firſt, you muſt beware, that if ſhee but once onely know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Lure, that you lure her no more, but once at one time, and let that ſuffice, although you take the more time to make her, which ſhall bee the more for her good; for otherwiſe it will hazard the ſpoyle of her, or any other <hi>Hawke</hi> you intend to make to the field; for ſo ſoone as
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:26902:66"/>
ſhee once knoweth the Lure, ſhee will ſettle her loue on it, and deſire to hold it, and will be loath to be taken vp from it to bee lured againe, and will quickly grow fearefull to let you or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man to come neare her, leſt ſhee ſhould be depriued of that which ſhee chiefely deſireth to enioy, and will dragge and couer to carie it from you.</p>
               <p>Alſo during the time of her luring and tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, you had need be carefull to order the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe ſo, as that ſhee may haue her reward, for the moſt part, at your hand in bits, onely reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſome ſmall quantitie to take her to your fiſt withall: and all this while you muſt haue your <hi>Spaniels</hi> cloſe by you, as ſhee is on the ground, and euery day acquaint them well together; for they bee <hi>Hawkes</hi> of all other that bee moſt coy and fearefull to ſuffer any dogges to come neare them.</p>
               <p>Alſo at her firſt entring you ought to haue but few dogges, and ſuch as be both coole and gentle, vntill ſhee bee well entred and alſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with them; and then ſhee will bee out of all danger, although ſhee ſhould afterwards at ſome times bee put beſides her prey, yet ſhee will not be beaten quite out of loue, or diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged therewith, but euen ſlightly will account of ſuch an accident, becauſe ſhee had beene ſo kindly vſed and nuzled amongſt them before; whereas otherwiſe for want of this kind of care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ordering and gouerning at the firſt, if ſhee
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:26902:67"/>
ſhould chance to take any fright or ſudden feare with a dogge, ſhee would neuer abide them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, being a <hi>Hawke</hi> ſo coy and apte vnto it, and alſo ſtrong and well able to carry her prey away: ſhee were quite and for euer made; for ſhee wil too ſoone know her owne ſtrength, and whenſoeuer ſhee ſhall haue a Partridge in her foote, ſhee will ſuffer neither man nor dogge to come neare her, but ſhee will carry it away and prey vpon it; which if ſhe ſhould doe but onely once, that is as much as one hundreth, for ſhee will neuer be reclaimed from it. And this is the onely fault the <hi>Ramage Lanner</hi> is ſubiect vnto, and alſo the beſt end of as many as falls not into a carefull, skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and painfull Faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coners hand.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:26902:67"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXV.</hi> Of the <hi>Ramage Lannner</hi> for the Riuer.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T cannot be denied but that there hath beene <hi>Hawkes</hi> of this kinde, both vpward and high flying, and alſo ſtowt and tough of their wings to maintaine the ſame. And I haue as often maruelled with my ſelfe what the reaſon ſhould be, that in my time no man (of my knowledge) hath euer made triall what per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection ſuch a <hi>Hawke</hi> might be brought vnto for the Riuer, conſidering they be alſo hardie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. Likewiſe I doe very well remember, that when I was but very young of yeares my
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:26902:68"/>
ſelfe, I heard an ancient Gentleman report, that in former times they were vſually flone there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, and were held in great eſtimation for the ſame; and in thoſe times the <hi>Haggart Faulcon</hi> was not knowne: He likewiſe affirmed that hee had a <hi>Lanner</hi> himſelfe that would flye very high and very long, euen like vnto the wilde <hi>Hobbie,</hi> the which was bred in Molton Parke: and in drawing through the young ſprings, himſelfe and his <hi>Spaniels</hi> in a Forreſt where hee liued, as he often vſed to doe, with his <hi>Hawke</hi> high flying ouer him, he hath ſometimes put vp fowle vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares vnto him that vſed to lye in plaſhie or waterie places in the ſaid Groues or buſhie clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the which ſhe would not miſſe, but kill one of them at her down come. Alſo at other times the Feſant cocke, the Woodcocke and the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trige; and for theſe things that I haue named, there could not any of them come to her amiſſe, ſuch was the excellency and goodneſſe hee had brought her vnto through his plaine and ſimple skill: for of my owne knowledge he was no Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coner, although he had ſome loue and little vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, as many others haue that likes well the ſport. Now if this were true, as I doe verily beleeue it was, for that hee was a man, as I haue told you, truely auncient, and of good reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: wherefore then ſhould not wee in theſe daies and times of more experience, &amp; greater knowledge, in ſome ſort, ſhake off this habit of ſloath &amp; idleneſſe that we haue been trained vp
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:26902:68"/>
and nuzled in this many yeares? and ſummon our wits and deuices together, not only to teach vs tread the path of our ancient friends, and imitate their inuentions, but alſo well to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaud them for the ſame with due reſpect to their inſtructions? But ſome man may replye and ſay,<note place="margin">The nouice.</note> Wherefore ſhould wee ſo much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble our ſelues with ſuch dull metled humours as they bee, that will aske ſo much labour and paines about them, before they can be brought to any perfection? There is the braue ſpirited <hi>Haggard Falcon Gentle,</hi> ſhee will bee reclaimed and made with a trice; and ſhee is of a louing diſpoſition, and alſo as franke and free of her mettle: and therefore if wee will beſtow on her but one three weekes, or a moneths well luring and training with Doues to cauſe her to loue vs, ſhee will be wholly wedded to vs, and will not away. And moreouer, ſhe will as ſodainely vnderſtand what ſhee ſhould doe; for ſhee will not require much inſtruction. And this is the bird worthy of due commendation. To the which ſaying I yeeld, and will ſay no leſſe, for I can no way wiſely diſpraiſe her; for if I ſhould, I muſt doe both my ſelfe great wrong, and her alſo, that before I haue ſo highly commended: but thus farre giue me leaue to anſwere, as it is in ſome ſort truely ſaid, and may alſo be as well performed with ſome <hi>Hawke,</hi> ſo is it on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, as ſlightly and ſimply anſwered; and it is as common in theſe dayes with euery nouice
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:26902:69"/>
of little or no vnderſtanding, that hath but new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie gotten his arte onely in fit tearmes and phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and for any other reaſon they haue or can alleage about ſuch a <hi>Hawke,</hi> or of what elſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs vnto her, but onely that common ſaying, by euery one of well louing the <hi>Haggart.</hi> I haue knowne in my time many ſhepheards reſorting to Hawking places, that I durſt haue vnderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to haue taught any of them with a few plaine inſtructions in one fortnight to haue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed as much ſo well as they, with ſome <hi>Hawke</hi> of the kinde, although there be ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the ſame generation that will put twenty wiſer men then they to their ſhifts: but I would very faine heare of one of theſe ſelfe conceited young men that would ſomewhat withdraw his affection from theſe kinde of <hi>Hawkes</hi> that are ſo eaſily, and with little paines reclaimed, and will in a manner as they ſuppoſe, euen make themſelues. I would ſee him to vndertake the <hi>Ramage Lanner,</hi> and with all his wiſedome make her ſeeme a Faulconers <hi>Hawke</hi> to the brooke, that will not make her ſelfe neyther be framed by another without both labour and skill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede: truely hee ſhould deſerue much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations for his well performing of this bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe; and more then for any ſuch wherein as hee deemes is not required much Art, paines, or any great attendance. And for him that will bend his minde, and will be willing to practiſe heerein, I will ſhew him my aduice, and the
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:26902:69"/>
beſt directions from my author, or owne vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that I may afford him.</p>
               <p>It is not vnknowne but that the beſt metled <hi>Hawke,</hi> and higheſt ſlier of any kinde, may bee abuſed and drawne downe farre from her won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted gate, as eyther with too much flying, or too hard feeding, as to be wearied, or as it were ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out with too often and ouermuch toyling, or otherwiſe with hauing too great an edge and appetite ſet on them with impoueriſhment, proceeding from too ſtraight a hand kept on them in their diet and feeding. And for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, the moſt of the <hi>Lanners</hi> kinde are ſpoyled theſe wayes, and drawne cleane from their wings, and forced to
<figure/>
flye about the mans head, and goe to ſtand, and therefore although they be all of a hard kinde, yet they are not all alike, but do differ in their natures as much as others doe, which ought to be well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected, and eſpecially noted, the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the good metled <hi>Hawke</hi> and the bad, and to be ordered thereafter, and yet not in any ſort it is meet they ſhould be ſtarued; for there is no <hi>Hawke,</hi> and eſpecially of this kinde, that is too much pinched, but will leaue and giue ouer
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:26902:70"/>
that thing which ſhe ſhould flye after, and take paines for, and more willingly returne backe to him againe that ſhee knowes well, hath, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo will, on little cauſe in the end reward her: and therefore when you haue your <hi>Hawke</hi> full and in good temper, the beſt courſe is and will bee for you ſo to keep her. And let her diet be ſuch, and the quantity thereof with a hand certaine and ſteadily kept on her;<note place="margin">Neither too much at one time, nor too little at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</note> as that it may main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine health and ſtrength to preſerue her; for hee that hath not ſo much diſcretion as to conſider of this order, and to gouerne and to vſe this <hi>Hawke</hi> thereafter, ſhall neuer haue her to flie cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely, but euen as ſhe is fed diſorderly, ſo ſhee will performe her ſeruice as careleſly. And this one other thing you ought to take notice of, which is, that as you doe firſt vſe theſe kind of <hi>Hawkes</hi> in their luring and training to their diet and feeding, ſo ſhall you for the moſt part finde by them in your further practiſe and dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with them. Therefore when you ſhall haue one of them to deale withall, and that in her ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king you doe finde her apt and forward to your liking, let her not be much pincht howſoeuer you doe in her diet and feeding: and alſo bee carefull to take good time in her training, with Doues giuen in a long creance for a while, that ſhee may kill them cloſe by you vntill her coy behauiour and wildneſſe be ouer, and ſhee bee growne familiar, and will ſuffer you without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny coyneſſe or ſtaring to come in to her: Alſo
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:26902:70"/>
let her be fed and rewarded of the ſame Doues ſhee kills, or with ſome other ſuch good meate, onely it beeing hot, let it be a little waſht as it were to giue a <hi>Faulcon,</hi> and no more; for you ſhal not need to carry ſo hard or ſtraight a hand as if you intended to flye her to the field. And with this courſe of ſo well making, and other ſuch neceſſary ordering, with caſting and ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as I haue formerly taught, belonging, you ſhall keepe her full, and lofty of life and ſpirit to hold her wings withall. And alſo if by nature there were euer any vpwardneſſe or high flying in her in the time of her wildneſſe, ſhe will both ſhew it and hold it, you may be aſſured of it; and then you may put her to the Riuer, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a good make-<hi>Hawke,</hi> you ſhall well quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie her, and then ſhe will be worthy the accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of; and the <hi>Faulconer</hi> that hath ſo made her ſhall haue his due praiſe and commendations for his labour and paines-taking ſo artificially with her: whereas otherwiſe if ſhe proue not a high flyer, yet there is no labor loſt; for ſhe may quickly change her dyet, and with a ſtraiter order cauſe her to ſcratch amongſt <hi>Spaniels</hi> for the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridge, which will alſo well counteruaile his labour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:26902:71"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVI.</hi> Of the <hi>Ramage Lanneret</hi> for the Riuer or Field.</head>
               <figure>
                  <head>LANNER.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is not much more to bee ſaid for the <hi>Ramage Lanneret,</hi> then hath beene heere preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, and is ſpoken of the <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner;</hi> for what method or order ſoeuer is meete and fitting for the one, the very ſame ſerueth directly for the other, and he alſo being well mand, loſed, trained and made inward to the man, may be alſo flone to the Riuer; for very many of them are very ſpiritfull and vpward <hi>Hawkes,</hi> and being well quarried, proueth very ſure &amp; certaine <hi>Hawkes,</hi>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:26902:71"/>
and good fowle-ſlayers, and are very fit to bee vſed as leaders.</p>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Hawkes</hi> ought to be kept as high and full of fleſh as may be, neuertheleſſe there ought ſpeciall regard to be had to the ſtomack alwaies, that with cleane feede, caſting, and ſtones often (that) may be held perfect to cauſe him main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and perform his ſeruice after the beſt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. But whoſoeuer can by his Art and labour beſt reclaime and make them to loue and be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar with the <hi>Spaniels</hi> he ſhall vſe, and eſteeme of them as moſt meeteſt for the field, and the equalleſt match for the Partridge, but they are for the moſt part very coy and fearefull of the <hi>Spaniels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet neuertheleſſe of my owne knowledge, if you can bee charie of them at the firſt entring, and vntill they be well blouded and in loue with their game, although afterward they ſhould ſometimes by an vnruly <hi>Spaniell</hi> be depriued of their prey, yet they will ſlightly account of it, and remaine neuertheleſſe ſtill conſtant in their loue to the thing they formerly tooke delight in, if you will remember,<note place="margin">The Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridge.</note> and alwaies be mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, as I haue often told you, of the ſtomacke, that it may be hot and fiery, which will compell them onely to minde their ſeruice, and not to regard the ſight of the dogs, or any other thing; for you muſt eſpecially conſider, and further be mindfull, that the Partridge time is in the ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, which is alwaies inclined to heate and hot
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:26902:72"/>
weather, and therefore you muſt feede ſo much the cleaner, and waſh the harder to hold him in true ſubiection withall; whereas otherwiſe the other ſport is in the winter, when as it is farre more ſharpe and colder: which muſt likewiſe be thought on, and your <hi>Hawke</hi> be ordered there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, and fed ſo much the better.</p>
               <p>And whoſo will attaine true vnderſtanding, ought euermore to be mindfull of the difference of times and ſeaſons, and well to obſerue them, and then hee ſhall bee well able to gouerne his <hi>Hawke</hi> by Art and diſcretion; whereas other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in being forgetfull thereof, or hauing little or no vnderſtanding of thoſe things, he ſhall not be able to rule them by reaſon; for being as they are birds of the ayre, which holds ſeldome certaine, they muſt be dieted and gouerned ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the changeable or conſtant temper of the ſeaſon, in ſommer or winter: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if you doe well bethinke your ſelfe, it is no eaſie matter, for euery one to order and gouerne certainely, ſuch (a body) and hold it alwaies in temper, that is ſo mutable, and euer altereth as the wether; but he muſt be expert in his Art, and alſo his Crafts-maſter: and ſo I will ceaſe to ſay any more of the <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage,</hi> and proceed to the <hi>Eyas,</hi> of the ſame kinde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:26902:72"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXVII. <hi>Of the</hi> Eyas Lanner, <hi>or</hi> Lanneret.</head>
               <figure>
                  <head>LANNER.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Will now conclude with the <hi>(Eyas Hawke)</hi> by which appeares a difference betweene them in their ſeuerall natures, as well as in their contrary names or titles; all which I ſhall not neede to ſpeake of any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this place, neyther would it be any whit auaileable ſo to doe, but will proceed as breefe as I may, and out of my owne knowledge and vnderſtanding, gathered euen by little practiſe and obſeruation, ſhew how ſhee ought to bee made ready to be flone to the field.</p>
               <p>And whereas I haue formerly aduiſed that in all ſorts and kindes of <hi>Hawkes</hi> you ought firſt to
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:26902:73"/>
conſider of their generation: Secondly in your further labour and practiſe to finde out their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and how therein they are inclined: and thirdly, that being rightly and well perceiued, then to frame and faſhion by Art and diſcretion your manner of courſe and dealing with them, according to the ſame. Likewiſe for this <hi>Hawke</hi> laſtly and particularly heere mentioned, you muſt conſider that ſhe was taken out of the neſt very young, and after cloſely kept, fed, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarly trained vp onely by the man, whereby of neceſſity ſhe muſt needs altogether forget her naturall damme that bredde her, and become louing and fond on him that brought her vp: Alſo this manner of breeding muſt needs cauſe her to differ much in the inclination of her bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy from the other, which as you haue heard were bred and trained vp by their damme after another faſhion. Wherefore as your former drift and deſire was only by your Art and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry to reclaime them from their wildneſſe,<note place="margin">The Hag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gart or Ramage Hawkes.</note> and draw their loues conſtantly vnto you. So now on the contrary you muſt bee as chary that in your teaching and training, you doe not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether beſot this <hi>Hawke,</hi> that is in her owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture too fooliſh and fond of you already.</p>
               <p>And for that I ſhall not need to preſcribe any rule or order for the reclaiming, luring, or any other thing concerning her firſt handling, I will proceed to the next inſtruction, which is this: when ſhee will come rudely to the lure garniſht
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:26902:73"/>
with meat, and alſo flye about you for the ſame: then let her kill two or three liue Doues at the Lure where they may haue ſome little ſcope to flicker and ſtirre about, whereby to giue her the more cauſe &amp; incouragement to come to them; which when ſhe will do readily, &amp; with an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deſire prey vpon them, let her haue no more after that faſhion; but the next time when ſhe is prepared well for it, let her bee lured from man to man, and as ſhee is comming giue her a field Doue in ſuch a creance as you know it cannot carry quite away from you: then if ſhe do rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and eagerly flye after that and kill it, let her bee well rewarded on it; but after that let her haue no more vpward traines giuen vnto her, nor any other that ſhee may ſee to come from the man; for they be ſuch things onely that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſots, and abſolutely ſpoyles all thoſe kinde of <hi>Hawkes.</hi> For in euery mans vnderſtanding that hath any diſcerning or obſeruing knowledge, their bodies bee tempered with mettle of ſuch induration, as that their owne natures will af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford and permit them euen to liue of any thing; which is the reaſon they want ſpirit and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and therefore are for the moſt part of a drowſie and dull diſpoſition; and what they are firſt taught and brought vnto, the ſame they will euerlaſtingly cleaue vnto, whether it bee good or bad, as to the very Lure and Hawking bag, with hauing or receiuing too much kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, although but in ſcraps from them; they
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:26902:74"/>
will bee ſo tied and intangled in their loue and deſire towards them, as that afterwards with all the paines, Art, and skill that a man hath, hee ſhall neuer bee able to withdraw their feruent loue ſo deepely planted there, to bee ſet on any other thing, or placed otherwhere.</p>
               <p>My meaning or intent is not to tye or binde you to this ſtrict limitation with euery <hi>Hawke,</hi> as iuſtly to appoint how many Doues to giue and no more; but ſtill do deſire that you ſhould be mindfull, and alwaies remember the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene the good metled <hi>Hawke</hi> and the bad, and ſo to vſe them in their training and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery other way; but how ſoeuer they ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to you, neuertheleſſe by my aduice giue as few traines as poſſible you may to any field <hi>Hawke</hi> of this kinde, for the foreſaid occaſions, but euen ſo ſoon as they be taught to catch firſt readily on the Lure, let them haue the reſt giuen vnſeild with ſome few feathers drawne from them, that they may kill them al-waies by the ground, without any mounting at all: Alſo from the fiſt, and out of the hood; and then ſo ſoone as ſhee will flye and truſſe readily that way, leaue off that courſe, and ſhew her Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridge, and if it bee poſſible, let her haue ſome few from the hand, after the ſame manner: and there is no queſtion but with this courſe rightly obſerued, and well followed, you may make e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the verieſt ſlug of the dulleſt ſpirit, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a good <hi>Hawke,</hi> as well for the field and the
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:26902:74"/>
Partridge, as otherwiſe to hold out and purſue a traine to the end from the mans hand.</p>
               <p>I know there will bee an expectation at my hand of ſome rules of Phyſicke for theſe kinde of <hi>Hawkes,</hi> and the beſt anſwere that I neede to make vnto it, is this: Firſt, there is no ſound <hi>Hawke</hi> whatſoeuer, that ſhall haue need of any ſuch thing, vnleſſe it bee to confound her, that otherwiſe would doe well; and for theſe kinde of <hi>Hawkes,</hi> it goes hard with them when they ſhall haue any ſuch occaſion: and therefore by my counſell, let euery man that hath his <hi>Hawke</hi> ſound and well, ſtriue and bee carefull to keepe her ſo; for it is farre more eaſier to doe ſo, then when he hath through negligence or euill order abuſed or put her out of temper, to amend her with Phyſicke againe neyther can he euer do it, vnleſſe in ſome appliment for an apparant out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward accident; but otherwiſe, for any inward medicine, let it be euen cleane feed, well waſht, and ſtones with diſcretion, and once in a weeke to the full and hard <hi>Hawke;</hi> and on a reſting day, ioyne ſome ſalendine with them, to cleanſe and purge her of ſuch glit, and other imperfection as thoſe <hi>Hawkes</hi> be moſt ſubiect vnto, and haue gathered, with reſt or full feeding before.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>LANNER.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>And whereas I haue heeretofore diſcourſed &amp; ſhewed ſufficiently of them in euery reſpect, as how to take them from the mew beeing fat and full, or otherwiſe from the cage, or elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, and how to order them accordingly without any medicine or ſcowring at all: And whereas many men holdes an opinion, that when they haue drawne their <hi>Hawke</hi> from the
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:26902:75"/>
mew, it is not poſſible to make her cleane and ready to flye without two or three ſcowrings in the meane while: I thinke I haue ſaid enough for that before, and alſo ſhewed farre a better way, and therefore I ſhall not neede to ſay any more in this place; and alſo let mee aduiſe euery young man that wiſhes well to the ſport, and would be a <hi>Faulconer,</hi> that hee doe neuer giue any manner of ſcowring or medicine to a ſound <hi>Hawke,</hi> how fat or full ſoeuer ſhee be; for there is an olde rule or ſaying in Phyſicke, which is, The whole needes no Phyſition: and for the <hi>Hawke</hi> I can maintaine it, for I neuer yet knew that euer it did good to any one, but otherwiſe hath much diſtempered them, and hazarded their liues; nay otherwiſe taken it quite away, that elſe before were in no danger at all. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, for that euery one is not of the ſame o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, but doth otherwayes diſpoſe of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and determine to practiſe on very little or no occaſion: I will here for ſuch greefes as theſe kinde of <hi>Hawkes</hi> be ſubiect vnto, ſet downe ſo many medicines, as through occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion I haue found by experience to be moſt conuenient and neceſſary to be applied or giuen vnto them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section_of_medicine">
               <pb facs="tcp:26902:76"/>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:26902:76"/>
               <head>Lathams <hi>approued medicines,</hi> incident to all <hi>Hawkes</hi> mentioned <hi>in this Booke.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="28" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXVIII.</hi> Of the cold in the head, or the <hi>Rye.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F all the diſeaſes that belongs to theſe <hi>Hawkes,</hi> there be one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly three that they be moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vnto, which is the <hi>Rye,</hi> the <hi>Cramp,</hi> and the <hi>Craye;</hi> and being once taken and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued any ſeaſon, they will be very hard euer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to bee recouered: Therefore the beſt way will be for the keeper euermore to be mindfull and carefull to preuent their infection, before a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them hath laid holde, or ſeazed on his <hi>Hawke;</hi> which he may very eaſily doe if hee will bee mindfull and watchfull ouer them, and through his foreſeeing knowledge bee carefull to auoid the occaſion. All theſe infirmities be in a manner taken one way, and proceede of one cauſe, which is cold, and after this manner they bee ingendred: the <hi>Crampe</hi> and the <hi>Rye</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth after the <hi>Hawke</hi> hath beene hard flone and laboured, eſpecially in the winter time, in wet and drye, when as afterward they bee ſet vp or
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:26902:77"/>
downe to reſt the night time, in ſome moiſt or dampe place, low, neere vnto ſome earthen floore; wherefore it is neceſſary that you be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore carefull to ſet them vp as high as you can in ſuch places, and vpon ſome thing or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that they may reſt warme vpon, after their bodies and bloud hath beene extraordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heat and chafed, to preuent that danger; for they will not brooke to ſit in the night time neere to the moiſt earth as other <hi>Hawkes</hi> will doe, and it hath oft times cauſed the <hi>Crampe</hi> to lay hold vpon euery ioynt and limme of the whole body; and for that I haue already written ſo largely of the ſame diſeaſe, and what may be done for the recouery of it, I will heere ſay no more, but that the beſt courſe is through care and diligence to ſeeke to preuent the comming of it. Alſo for the <hi>Rye</hi> that is taken through the ſame occaſion, and is a faſt-ſetled griefe &amp; ſtuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing in the head; and will, if it be not quickly found, and as ſodainely lookt vnto, grow ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to a drie frownce or a wet, or otherwiſe a continuall moiſt humour, which will hardly be euer cured; for example, I had a <hi>Hawke</hi> ſent me the laſt Michaelmas from Sir <hi>William Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes,</hi> winking of one eye, the which proceeded of a continuall cold in the head as I plainly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued; and after I had a little looſened it by one couer that was growne in the cheſt of his Pallat, and another cloſe by his eare, on the ſame ſide that he winked on, which I took away; and alſo
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:26902:77"/>
was inforced to burne one of his nares to open that which was quite ſtopt vp, I vſed all the meanes I could to purge and cleanſe it, and hee ceaſed not euery other day to throw and caſt out ſome filth, and in time ſo much, as it is not to be imagined or ſpoken of, during the time vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till after the Chriſtmas following, and then it ceaſed and dried vp on the ſodaine. This plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhewes what a fault and ouer-fight it is in any man that wil not when he may, ſo eaſily preuent ſuch things before they doe come, or otherwiſe when they are taken to be careles and vnmind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to eſpie them, but to let them run and grow on vntill they be vnrecouerable; therfore when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer you ſhall by any meanes haue ſuch a <hi>Hawke</hi> that is any whit ſtuft in the head, look that you defer no time to breake it, leſt further or the like inconuenience doe grow thereon as I haue ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you, and for recouery thereof, this will be your beſt courſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="29" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:26902:78"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXIX.</hi> Of the <hi>Rye</hi> or ſtuffing in the Head.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, you muſt bee very carefull that ſhe may alwaies ſit warm, and eſpecially in the night time &amp; alſo that ſhe may euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more be fed with hot meat, and fire as often as may be, for it likewiſe giue her now and then at euening with her meat, 2. or 3. bruiſed cloues of mace; the which is one very good thing againſt the ſame diſeaſe, and will alſo ſweetly perfume her whole body and breath, and ſharpen her appetite: alſo vſe her to freſh butter that hath beene quickly gathered, and ſhall be well clarified ouer a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing-diſh of coales, with a little Rue and Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron in powder, and good ſtore of Sugarcandie well tempered altogether; let her haue this with her meate euermore a little at a time, and it will preſently looſen her, and cauſe her to ſnite and throw with her head; which when you perceiue, then take the iuyce of Dazie rootes, and with a ſtraw blow it hard into her nares a pretty while before you intend to feede her; then afterward when ſhe is at quiet againe, let her haue her din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:26902:78"/>
in her foot that ſhe may lyer well on it, and this will certainly amend her; for although this iuice of Dazies is a common medicine, yet it will purge and cleanſe the head being looſened be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as well as any thing whatſoeuer. Blow into her nares with a ſtraw, the iuyce of Sage three mornings in the weeke; it is very good to draw downe tough ſlime out of the head. I could ſet downe diuers other things more ſtronger, but in them there is ſome danger; and in this there is none at all, but will worke to good purpoſe, and cauſe a good concluſion.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="30" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:26902:79"/>
                  <head>CHAP. XXX. <hi>Of the</hi> Craye.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His diſeaſe or infirmity that wee call or terme the <hi>Craye,</hi> is of an exiccatiue or aſtringent qualitie, drying &amp; binding in the <hi>Hawke,</hi> which cauſeth her not to mute or ſlice from her according as naturally ſhee ought to doe, but otherwiſe to drop farre ſhort ſome part of it diſperſt aſunder from the other; &amp; alſo paſſes not clearely with eaſe, but comes harſhly and hardly from her; all which ſignes and ſhewes are apparant and eaſie to bee percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. And therefore the keeper is ſo much the more to be blamed that ſhall deferre any time, and ſuffer the cure thereof to be neglected; for by that meanes the griefe is growne to be more dangerous and deadly: whereas otherwiſe it is of no moment, but may bee very eaſily amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; for you are to remember that this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar infirmity proceedes alſo of cold, as the other doth that I haue before named, but yet after a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother faſhion: For I let you know before, that both the <hi>Crampe</hi> and the <hi>Rye</hi> commeth by taking cold: And this which now I ſpeake of, is taken by a continuance of groſſe and cold waſht meat
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:26902:79"/>
that is giuen the <hi>Hawke</hi> to feede vpon, which this kinde will not endure or laſt withall; for it will conſume them inwardly where it cannot be ſeene, as in thoſe places, and after the manner as ſhall appeare heereafter plaine vnto you. It is not vnknown but that the gorge of the <hi>Hawke</hi> is the firſt place and onely receptacle or harbor of ſuch ſuſtenance as ſhee alwaies takes to nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh her whole body withall, and is vnto her as a maine and cleane conduit, the which being fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with pure &amp; cleare liquor, it is not tainted or made vnſauorie there, but let paſſe in due time further into ſmaller veſſels, more fine then it was before, to ſerue for other vſes: Euen ſo on the contrary it is with the <hi>Hawke;</hi> for if her gorge be filled with ſtale and groſſe colde meat, contrary to her naturall inclination, it will ſoone grow vnſauory there, and her ſtomacke will abhorre to entertaine it, and alſo the other more ſecret paſſages will be annoyed thereby, which will quickely turne to her deſtruction. As for example, I haue knowne diuers <hi>Hawkes</hi> that hath died on this occaſion, whoſe inward and inuiſible infirmity hath neuer beene miſtruſted, but onely hath practiſed and wrought on the tuel for remedie; neuertheleſſe when ſhee hath beene opened, the very gorge hath beene like vnto chawke with the panell, and the next ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting place into the ſmall guts hath beene euen burnt &amp; eaten with heat like vnto the Frownce, which was the cauſe her excrements wanted
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:26902:80"/>
free paſſage: all which proceede from ſuch vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall ſtale diet as the ſtomacke could not wel brooke, and were repugnant to their naturall diſpoſition; for there is no ſuch kinde of groſſe feede giuen, although the gorge will with gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe receiue it, yet afterwards the ſtomacke will be choyce and vnwilling to taſte of it, as you may well perceiue when it hath beene kept ſo long as that it begins to waxe windie, ſowre, &amp; diſtaſtfull, and by the courſe of nature would faine be eaſed and emptied of ſome part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which doth ſo much annoy and offend her; as you may ſee by her often writhing and ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to remoue it, and put it downe into the pannell:<note place="margin">Her ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke.</note> and when ſhe hath in ſome meaſure ſo done, through nature<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> violent forcing, yet it is alſo therein ſo long detained, and vnkindly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted, as that by vertue of it, ſhee doth not win to her ſelfe any naturall or kindly comfort; but otherwiſe euill imperfections and humours of moyſture doth ariſe thereon, which aſcends vp into the head, whereby all that part is moleſted: otherwiſe there is left downewards much vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall heate and oppilations or ſtoppings that infects the body and ſecret paſſages; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon this diſeaſe which we call the <hi>Craye</hi> doth proceed, with many others. Wherefore it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houeth euery man to reſpect his <hi>Hawke</hi> better, then at any time to cloye or clog her with ſuch groſſe and vnkindly feeding, but otherwiſe with care to giue her her due as neere as hee may,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:26902:80"/>
according to her deſeruing and naturall diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; withall further obſeruing other ſuch ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary courſes belonging in due time and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as I haue in many places appointed by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions, and in ſo doing hee ſhall neuer haue neede to take care for eyther ſcowring or medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, but ſhall euermore haue his <hi>Hawke</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his owne liking, full lofty and ſtrong, well able to performe her buſineſſe after the beſt manner; whereas the other that ſhall be careleſſe and forgetfull, &amp; is well pleaſed if he may pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per her with any thing, and is as vnreſpectiue of other wants or needs appertaining: hee ſhall ſeldome or neuer haue his <hi>Hawke</hi> perfect and healthfull, but euer out of tune and vnfitte to doe any thing; whereas before through ill dyet and diſorder your <hi>Hawke</hi> caught this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, ſo now on the contrary, and eſpecially, by meanes of better vſage and good diet, with ſome other appliment, you muſt reſtore her to health againe: wherefore ſo ſoone as it is perceiued, you muſt remember that you are not onely to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy and kill the <hi>Craye</hi> alone, but alſo ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther euils as waites and partakes with that in the vnnaturall working the poore <hi>Hawkes</hi> deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is cold and moiſt, raw humours aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending vp into the head, and otherwiſe vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall heat and drowth, with oppilations or ſtoppings poſſeſſing the body and interior paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages; all which ought to be particularly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered of, and your remedy prepared and appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:26902:81"/>
accordingly. Then firſt you muſt bethinke your ſelfe of her diet, that it may be of light and coole meates, eaſie to be diſgeſted, as of Hens fleſh, Chickens, young Pigeons, Rabbets, new Sheepes-hearts, Porke, Pig of the ſhoulder and the heart: then muſt you prouide the ſweeteſt freſh butter of the neweſt gathering that may be, and boyle and ſcum it well with halfe a ſcore bruiſed cloues of mace in it; and when you haue ſo done, in the cooling put in a little of the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Rue, and ſo keepe it cloſe in a boxe, and as often as you doe feed, anoint her meat there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, the oftner the better, ſo that the gorges be eaſie, according to the <hi>Hawkes</hi> abilitie, and the power of the infirmitie: and for certaine, this will not faile onely to open and looſen the head, but alſo diſperſe thoſe other humors in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and ſcower them away that was cauſe of the ſundrie diſeaſes. Now when you haue ſeen this buſineſſe thus well effected in the head by her countenance and other appearance there; and alſo that ſhee mutes and ſlices well from her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, neuertheleſſe it may well be her head was but onely looſened, will haue ſome need alſo to be better purged, and clearely cleanſed. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe for the body &amp; inward paſſages, although they were or are newly ſcowred, yet neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they may require ſome more labor therein, and alſo to be throughly cooled. Therefore, as you ſhall ſee cauſe, firſt in the head by ſnufling or ſniting, or any other ſignes, vſe the iuyce of
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:26902:81"/>
Daſies or Sage, to cauſe her throw it forth the ſooner; but if you perceiue the humour to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue neuertheleſſe moiſt ſtill, then put to the iuyce a little of the powder of duſt of Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone to drie it vp withall, and ſhe ſhall doe well. Likewiſe for the body and inward places, giue with her meate the diſtilled water of eyther Horehound or Woodbine, or the water of Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, that I haue preſcribed in my other booke, and ſhee ſhall be well, and her body moderately cooled, and in good temper againe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="31" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. XXXI. <hi>Of the</hi> Eye.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>Goſhawke</hi> as you know is a fierce ſpirited, &amp; faſt flying <hi>Hawke</hi> if ſhe haue naturally a true loue and liking to her prey: and for that ſhee is moſt commonly vſed to flye through the hight of higheſt and thickeſt woods, where the game that ſhee beſt loues, moſt often vſes; and becauſe the eye and onely ornament of her body is her chiefe guide in thoſe places, and is ſo deare and precious a Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell vnto her, it were great pitty that it ſhould miſcarry or bee blemiſht by any misfortune. Therefore fearing or miſdoubting that any ſuch euill accident ſhould befall, I will ſhew you a ſure medicine to amend it withall.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="32" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="140" facs="tcp:26902:82"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXXII.</hi> For the <hi>Eye</hi> that ſhall haue any hurt by accident or otherwiſe to grow vpon it.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ake a thunderbolt, the which is found moſt commonly in the fields, in ſome channell or water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, by which means it is there laid open from the earth, and is eaſily to be perceiued, and put it into a hot fire and burne it well; then when it is cold againe, beat it to fine powder, and ſearce or ſift it through a faire linnen cloath, then min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle it with ſweet butter in differently, and on any occaſion put as much or the quantity of two little pins heads morning and euening into the <hi>Hawkes</hi> eye; and if any thing whatſoeuer will doe it good, this will not faile to doe the like. Alſo you may at theſe times blow it into the eye with a ſtraw, and it is as good, and will as ſpeedily worke any thing forth, or recouer any thing that is growing, or amiſſe in that place.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="33" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="141" facs="tcp:26902:82"/>
                  <head>CHAP. XXXIII. <hi>Of the</hi> Hobby <hi>and the</hi> Marlion.</head>
                  <figure>
                     <head>HOBBY.</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>MERLIN.</head>
                  </figure>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is yet this Caſt of little <hi>Hawkes,</hi> the which I haue not ſo much as once named; the one is belonging to the young man, the other pertaining to the Lady: and in my opinion are moſt equally matcht one with the other, in regard whereof, it were great pitty they ſhould bee parted euer, but euen flye for the prey by turnes together; not you know where, I do not meane, for then the young man perforce muſt mount aloſt indeed, at which the Lady would be as lowly diſpleaſed to ſee her <hi>Marlion</hi> ſo put downe in the loſty flight: But what do I meane
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:26902:83"/>
to skip ſo farre beyond my Art? let mee curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly craue pardon and fauor, to leaue the Lady and her <hi>Hawke</hi> together, as birds with whom I neuer had, nor haue no skill to deale at all; and withdraw the young man and his <hi>Hobbie</hi>
                     <q>
                        <l>Into the Champian fields, where he</l>
                        <l>may be partaker of ſuch ſundry ſorts of glee,</l>
                        <l>As tongue can no way well expreſſe,</l>
                        <l>or eye ſhall ſeldome ſee;</l>
                        <l>For there he may behold her,</l>
                        <l>firſt as ſhe is wilde,</l>
                        <l>And ſee how ſhe beſtirs her,</l>
                        <l>the ſilly birds for to beguild:</l>
                        <l>And alſo attends the <hi>Falconer,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>and his <hi>Spaniels</hi> as they range,</l>
                        <l>As if ſhee were mand before,</l>
                        <l>which is a thing moſt ſtrange,</l>
                        <l>That ſuch a bird</l>
                        <l>that neuer was in hand,</l>
                        <l>Should wait ſo long, and ſtop ſo oft,</l>
                        <l>
                           <note place="margin">Many a true labouring ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hath been caſt off with a bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that hath deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued a Larke for his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</note>and neuer goe to ſtand.</l>
                        <l>And furthermore,</l>
                        <l>neither to bee ſerued,</l>
                        <l>But ſo let goe without reward</l>
                        <l>that hath ſo well deſerued.</l>
                        <l>Yet neuertheleſſe this louing <hi>Hawke</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>will take no offence at all,</l>
                        <l>But on the morrow next will as ready be</l>
                        <l>to come when hee ſhall call:</l>
                        <l>But to vncouple his <hi>Spaniels</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>after his wonted guiſe,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="143" facs="tcp:26902:83"/>To ſpring the fearefull Partridge</l>
                        <l>that in the ſtubble lies:</l>
                        <l>Or elſe the mounting Larke,</l>
                        <l>which ſoone the <hi>Hobbie</hi> ſpies,</l>
                        <l>And beats from ground with all her might</l>
                        <l>vp to the lofty skies;</l>
                        <l>Which then for to behold,</l>
                        <l>no mirth you may compare,</l>
                        <l>Vnto the <hi>Hobbie</hi> and the Larke,</l>
                        <l>thus ſtriuing in the ayre.</l>
                        <l>Vntill the harmeleſſe bird</l>
                        <l>being wearied with the flight,</l>
                        <l>Is forc't with clipped wings together,</l>
                        <l>to throw her ſelfe downe right.</l>
                        <l>Whereat the <hi>Hawke</hi> doth ioy,</l>
                        <l>and dallies by the way,</l>
                        <l>Yet long before they come to ground,</l>
                        <l>ſhee makes of her a prey.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the Partridge, the <hi>Haggart</hi> of this kinde is beſt, and may moſt certainely be made a ſpeciall <hi>Hawke</hi> for the ſame; ſhee muſt bee taught and trained in each degree like vnto the <hi>Faulcon;</hi> and muſt bee carefull not to flye her after eight a clocke in the morning, eſpecially if the Sunne breake out in any heate; for if you doe, ſhe will fall to ſoring and be loſt, and muſt be ſought vp againe where ſhee was firſt taken. Alſo in the afternoone you may begin at two, if the day be temperate, and <hi>Hawke</hi> with her vntill it be neere the ſetting of the Sunne; but if ſhe be flone any
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:26902:84"/>
longer, ſhe will likewiſe fall to dorring, and be loſt, but otherwiſe with this obſeruation and good order in her diet, ſhee will ſhewe her ſelfe a <hi>Hawke</hi> to pleaſe a Prince; for you may flye her twenty times in the afternoone, when no other <hi>Hawkes</hi> will flye but muſt be waited on: yet a little longer, then may you put her to it, as eyther to the Partridge, the quaile, the clot bird in the fallow fields which is a very fat and a dainty bird much like vnto the Martine, the Warwinckle, which is a pyed bird, and vſes moſt in paſtur-ground, or other champane places, whereas growes great and tall buſhes, one ſome place or diſtance from the other; whereas I haue ſeene an hundred ſtoopings vpon one of the ſame birds before it could be kild, which is moſt excellent ſport, and full of delight; for if the buſhes ſtands not ſome reaſonable diſtance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, the bird will be ſo terrified at the ſight of the <hi>Hobbie,</hi> as you may almoſt take it with your hand, and when you thinke it meete, in the end you may kill it with a ſtone bow, and throw it to the <hi>Hawke.</hi> Alſo for the Larke I am not able with my pen to expreſſe the delight and paſſing pleaſure that is in that flight, but indeede the <hi>Eyas</hi> is the very beſt for the mount; for after ſhe hath but wrought three or fowre ſeeled Larkes and preyed on them, ſhee will neuer giue ouer, but worke into the high ayre after the Larke, ſo it be in a champane and plain country; for there the policie and drift of the bird that nature hath
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:26902:84"/>
taught her, is, by being ſo exceeding high, and vpon a circle or wide turne of the <hi>Hobbie,</hi> to ſtretch away to ſome kinde of couert to ſhrowd and ſuccour her ſelfe thereby, by which meanes ſometimes they are preſerued from their merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe enemy, but more often are deceiued and doe loſe their liues in the mid-way.</p>
                  <p>When you are diſpoſed to haue one of theſe <hi>Hawkes</hi> to make to this flight, you muſt make your choyce of the formall, and take her from the neſt a little before ſhe is able to ſit vpon the ſide of the ſame; then muſt you prouide and make another neſt, and place it on ſome tree in eyther Orchard or Garden, where it may bee ſafe; and there ſhee muſt be fed by the man with bits giuen on the ſharpe end of a ſticke, vntill ſhe be growne able to ſtand ſtiffely on her legs, and to pull hard for the meate ſhee ſhall eate; at which time, as you ſhal further find her ſtrength and ableneſſe, the neſt being no higher but that a man may well reach it, ſhe muſt be taught by your Art and voyce in luring, to come to the lure from thence, if it be but a foote at a time at the firſt, and ſo afterward by degrees, as you doe finde her more ſtronger, to teach her to come further; and after this manner ſhe muſt be tute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vntill ſhee will come from the neaſt to your voyce ſo farre as ſhee can heare, and flye vpon you, attending ſtill on her wings where you will haue her, and vntill you perceiue her to be full ſound, when as you muſt haue your hood,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:26902:85"/>
Ieſſebuites and bells, with other ornaments be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to decke and furniſh her withall; which being done, ſhe muſt be made more gentle and acquainted with the hood, and carriage conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually on the fiſt: then muſt you prouide ſome Larkes to traine her withall, but not one to bee ſeene come from the fiſt or hand, but hauing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore kild two or three on the lure, let her goe at firſt from the hood to a trayne that muſt be in a creance of browne thred, and as high as a tall tree before you doe vnhood her to it. When as you ſhall finde her ſo apt and forward to that ſport, as by that time ſhee hath but inioyed two or three after that manner, ſhee will goe to her buſineſſe ſo willingly, and with ſuch delight and pleaſure, as it would euen rauiſh the minde and ſences of her keeper, or other ſpectator; then ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thus well taught and trained her, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward when you do not vſe or flye her, you may ſuffer her to take her pleaſure abroad both day and night continually, or as you ſhall ſee cauſe, alwaies remembring that you feede her not at home for a while at the firſt, but otherwiſe by your lure or voyce to draw her abroad ſome quarter or halfe mile, and there feede and leaue her; And for certain, when ſhe hath fed, feaked, and reioyced, ſhee will repaire ſodainely backe to the place where ſhe was bred vp by the man, and trained. Alſo, on reſting daies when ſhe is gorged, if you will obſerue her, you ſhall ſee her vſually in the heat of the day to flye and ſoare
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:26902:85"/>
ſo high, as it will not be poſſible to view or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold her; by which meanes with her naturall education together, ſhee will bee as perfect in knowledge of the country, as the wilde <hi>Haggart</hi> her naturall damme that bred her, and you ſhall not need after to fear to loſe or leaue her behind you any where within foure or fiue miles, with her prey in her foote, but ſo ſoone as ſhee hath concluded, ſhee will returne to the place of her firſt training againe. And this courſe ſhee will hold moſt certaine and conſtantly vntill the weeke before Michaelmas, but no longer, and then ſhe will as her owne nature ſhall leade her, be gone, if you giue her any liberty, and truſt her abroad.</p>
                  <p>But to return to the <hi>Haggart,</hi> as there be ſome of them excellent for this ſlight of high moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, ſo likewiſe there are other ſome that in their naturall vnderſtanding and cunning will deſire and ſeeke after aduantage, as to be high flowne on their wings, and from them, and after that manner to conquer their prey, but otherwiſe will not goe from the fiſt to the mowtie at all: alſo for their diet, it would bee of cleane waſht mutton or ſuch other like meate, when they flye not; for they be as hard <hi>Hawkes</hi> as any be, and muſt be ſtoned and ſet to a ſound ſtomack when they ſhould flye. And ſo I will leaue them as the moſt rare and excellent birds of the world for the young mans vſe, who cannot wel brook or endure to be tied to any certainety, as to bee
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:26902:86"/>
limited or appointed by preſcription, when or at what times he ſhal begin or end his ſport and pleaſure in Hawking.</p>
                  <p>Whereas altogether through the perſwaſion of my friends, I conſented at firſt, though vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to vndertake this buſineſſe, euen ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward, as vnaduiſedly and raſhly, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny foreſight, or conſideration of the ſubiects I was to treat of, or ground whereon I might ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly build my foundation, I haue laboured and trauelled a long time, vneaſily, and with much wearines in my iourney; neuertheleſſe am now well refreſhed and comforted that I wandred not from the line that was laid me, or the rough or rugged path that was likewiſe appointed to direct me: and therefore if I may with ſimple requeſt perſwade thee honeſt Reader, not to grudge at my good will, but cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure better of mee, I ſhall hartily thanke thee for thy loue, and ſo I ſit downe to reſt mee.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:26902:86"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Epilogue,</hi> Wherein is contained the opinion of a worthy Diuine <hi>S. I.</hi> and compoſed by himſelfe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this and the like ſubiect.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Haue alwaies thuoght <hi>Hunting</hi> &amp; <hi>Haw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,</hi> and the like exerciſes indifferent, with zealous<note n="a" place="margin">In the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures vpon the Hebrewes.</note> 
               <hi>Deering,</hi> perſwading my ſelfe that the ſmelling of the <hi>Dogge,</hi> the flying of the <hi>Hawke,</hi> the Antipathie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the Creatures, how euer it was produced by the fall of man, yet neuertheleſſe that God in his mercy al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, &amp; in his wiſe prouidence diſpoſeth euen of theſe contrarieties and Antipathies, as well as of the Sympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies of the creatures, for the good and vſe of <hi>man,</hi> his Lieutenant &amp; Vicegerent ouer the works of his hands. And for <hi>Hunting,</hi> more ſpecially it is my opinion (if not iudgement) that<note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 27. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Iſaack</hi> would not haue tollerated, much leſſe commanded <hi>Eſaus hunting,</hi> if it had bin ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Secondly, it is lawfull to kill the Creature in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian liberty, <hi>Deere</hi> or <hi>Hare,</hi> or the like, for meat or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine: yea ſo to kill them as they may be moſt vſefull &amp; behoofefull for man, which is done better by chaſe or courſe, then eyther by <hi>Gins</hi> or <hi>ſhooting</hi> (as experience ſhewes:) and (as ſome ſcrupulouſly obiect) this is not to tyrannize ouer the creature, in putting it by continuance of chaſe or courſe, to a more laſting paine, but rather to leſſen (euen as he that dies by degrees in a conſumption, or that bleeds to death, dies more eaſily then hee that is hewn with a ſword, as <hi>Samuel</hi> did<note n="c" place="margin">1 Sam. 15.33.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Agag,</hi> al at once:) wel the ground being the legitimation of this exerciſe, as many arguments may conuince, if it ſhould be contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted (the circumſtances of time, place, perſons, dulie and truly obſerued): now becauſe theſe exerciſes are groſſely and ſinfully abuſed by many looſe &amp; licentious perſons,
<pb facs="tcp:26902:87"/>
that obſerue no circumſtances (which vſually make or marre the actions) they vſing it moſt that ſtand leaſt need; in reſpect of any calling or imploiment they haue, or vndertake, to wearie their ſpirits, or ſpend their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die or braine, hauing their hearts ſo taken vp, and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions intangled with it, as they ſpend and miſpend their golden and pretious time, two or three whole daies in a weeke, making recreation halfe, if not all their vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, trade, and occupation, turning all their meate into ſauce, yea the Sabboth it ſelfe, which ſhould be dedicated to God and good duties, being prophaned and polluted by the diſcourſes of their chaſes and courſes with their hounds and horſes, or courſers; I ſay, becauſe ſuch idle libertines doe abuſe this honeſt and harmeleſſe exerciſe, as it hath euer beene accounted,<note n="d" place="margin">Romanis ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne viris opus, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile famae, vitae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> &amp; membris, &amp;c. <hi>Horace.</hi> Lege Natalem Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitem de venat. in fine Mythiolog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> may it not therefore be lawfully and conſcionably vſed with moderation by a <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> or <hi>Miniſter,</hi> or <hi>Lawyer,</hi> or <hi>Student,</hi> or any other ſeriouſly imployed, which in any function heat their braines, waſt their bodies, weaken their ſtrength, weary their ſpirits; that as a meanes (and bleſſing from God) by it their decayed ſtrength may be reſtored, their vitall and animall ſpirits quickned, refreſhed, and reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; their health preſerued, and they better inabled (as a bow vnbended for ſhooting) to the diſcharging of theſe weighty charges impoſed vpon them. Who will denie this, but eyther thoſe that are blockiſhly ignorant, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly or blindly zealous, viciouſly profane, ſplenitiuely malicious, or critically, if not hypocritically cenſorious? that will be taxing and condemning, and ſhooting their <hi>bruta fulmina,</hi> fooliſh Bolts as madde men their darts, againſt thoſe whom they hate or emulate, whether there be cauſe or no.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:26902:87"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
